<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A short inuentory of certayne idle inuentions the fruites of a close and secret garden of great ease, and litle pleasure. By C.T.</title>
            <author>Thimelthorpe, C.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1581</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 162 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 79 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13666</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23952.3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S111413</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99846765</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99846765</idno>
            <idno type="VID">11754</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13666)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 11754)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 538:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A short inuentory of certayne idle inuentions the fruites of a close and secret garden of great ease, and litle pleasure. By C.T.</title>
                  <author>Thimelthorpe, C.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 68, [2] leaves : ill. (woodcut)  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In Fleet-street by Thomas Marsh,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1581.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"The compositor to the auctour", on L2v, calls the author "Thimelthorpe".</note>
                  <note>Partly in verse.</note>
                  <note>Identified as 23952+ on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of a photostat of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Conduct of life --  Early works to 1900.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:11754:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11754:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SHORT Inuentory of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne Idle Inuentions</p>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> THE Fruites of a cloſe and ſecret Garden of great eaſe, and litle pleaſure.</p>
            <p>By C. T.</p>
            <p>IMPRINTED AT London in Fleet-ſtreet by Thomas Marſh.</p>
            <p>1581.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:11754:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11754:2"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> TO THE <hi>RIGHT VVORSHIP<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FVLL I. R.</hi> C. T. WISH<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ETH LONGE AND proſperous lyfe, to the glory and pleaſure of <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty GOD.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter I had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtovved ſome parte of my inforced ydle time in draw<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing theſe few and friuolous lynes of moſt vayne and y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle inuentions, onely of purpoſe to occupy my mynd, which otherwiſe, by occaſions vvas ſubiect to receyue a more troubleſome &amp; greater incom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>brance: and then bending my ſelfe to a further intent, to beſtow the ſowre fruictes of theſe my ydle gatheringes (thoughe from a place of ſmall plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure)
<pb facs="tcp:11754:3"/> of ſome ſuch of my friendes, whoſe curteſye I ſuppoſed woulde vouchſafe very wel to accept of them and in euery perticular poynt to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my folly: knowing that a litle mite was as wel accepted at the poore wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans hands, comming with a willing mynde, as the great and coſtly prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t was at the handes of the rich. I the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſetled my ſelfe vnto a further conſide<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ration, and this I wayghed and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered with my ſelfe, if I ſhould raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly take vppon me to ſend vnto one or two, or many of my friends, this litle bu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dle of trifling toyes: not vnlike but in a ſhort time it might be drawn fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one friende to an other, and ſo at the lenghth cleane out of the hands of my frendes, into the mouthes of ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, where perhappes it may bee ſo champt &amp; mumbled, as it ſhal cleane be altered from the deace<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t forme and ſhape of mans meate, and made loth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome to the ſight of euerye man, and onley fitte for the mouth of the Hogg. Wherby (beyng deſyrous to proceede
<pb facs="tcp:11754:3"/> in my purpoſe) I toke occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to enter into the imagination of the nature &amp; diſpoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with this intent, that if happily I could find the ciuil &amp; ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt inclinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of ſome, able to waigh in equal ballance, &amp; cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teruaile with the vnciuil, &amp; diſhoneſt diſpoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of o<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thers, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> would I y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more willingly be bold to aduenture y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> publiſhing hereof to ſome of my frends, according to my former meanig: &amp; now after a litle de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therin, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as the faulk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, who preſently after euery flight, doth hye and haſten hymſelfe to take the fruicts of his game from the foote of his hauke: I in the lyke maner cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge my wittes togeather, haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ded a iuſt accompt of them what they haue gathered accordyng to my purpoſe, to ſerue my turne, or at the leaſt to reſolue my mynde, and as the Hauke doth open hys foote to yeelde the pray vnto his mayſter, ſometyme very e gentlye, and ſometyme not ſo eaſelye, wythout ſome ſtryuinge, and wreſtynge: euen ſo alſo haue
<pb facs="tcp:11754:4"/> they in the ſame manner, accordinge to their ſkill now opened themſelues in this ſort vntome, as hereafter follo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>weth.</p>
            <p>According to your appointment wee haue beſtowed ſome time in trauay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and wandringe to and froe, and haue not onely traue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt the large and wyld field of this world, but as neare as wee coulde, haue alſo beaten euery little ſcrubbe and buſhe, wherein to our iudgementes any likely hoode of any thinge was to bee ſeene, whych poſſibly might ſerue your turne. And now as touching thoſe things vvhych at this tyme doe onely concerne our charge, and ſerue for your purpoſe, which onely bee pennes and tongues, thus much wee haue gathered togea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the behauiour &amp; diſpoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therin. In y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> field we haue ſene to the plaine ſight of the worlde, that there bee a very greate and infynite number of menne ſome wyth pennes in they r eares, bendynge themſelues onely vnto vvrightinge, ſome wyth
<pb facs="tcp:11754:4"/> bookes in their hands, and with great delighte beſtowinge all theyr tyme wholly in ſtudye. Some others vvee fynde neyther with Pen, nor Booke, but only with a lump of fleſh in their mouthes, ſo reſtles, as it ſeemeth ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom or neuer will<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent to take any reſt: of theſe ſome be reſtles onely of zeale &amp; erneſt good wil, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually to do good, or els of pleaſure to recreat themſelues or delight their Fryends, withoute vtterynge at any tyme any cauſe of offence: ſome others agayne with their naturall and mother witts do alwais buſy &amp; beate their braines, and moſt vainly occupy their tougues onely in carpinge and ſnatching, (do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nothing themſelues) continually at other mens doinges. On the other ſyde, of thoſe which geue their minds onely vnto wrightinge, we fynde the diſpoſitions of them bee alſo diuerſe, ſome to ſet forth and make playne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ignoraunt and common people continually the heauenly and deuine miſteryes, onely for the pleaſure and
<pb facs="tcp:11754:5"/> comfort to the Soule of man, ſome to wryghting of ſuch neceſſary matters, which onely touch and concerne a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth, beyng as needful for go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment, as the other is neceſſarye for comfort other ſome onely touch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g the ſafe keping and healthful preſerua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion of mans body, which be the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions. But leauinge to report any further vnto you, of neceſſarye wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, we fynd an other kynde of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in the plaine and open field, which geue themſelues very often to write of pleaſure, only to refreſh ſomtimes the weary witts as wel of themſelues, as of diuers other men, beyng perhaps long incombred before, with matters of greatter wayght, which for recrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſake was neuer thought a thinge greatly amiſſe. Of theſe we fynd ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry many, which do greatly pleaſe and delyght the humoure of the common people, without any iuſt cauſe of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence at all, more vnto one man then to another.</p>
            <p>And now to report vnto you no other
<pb facs="tcp:11754:5"/> vvyſe in euery poynt then according to truth, vvee cannot iuſtly ſay, that in the open field wee haue ſeene anye honeſt or wyſe man, that will take v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon him by his penne willingly to iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtefye anye vndecent, diſhoneſt, or vncomelye thynge, as wel for mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyes ſake, as for the preſeruation &amp; ſafe keepinge of their credits: for they know <hi>Litterae ſcriptae mane<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t,</hi> that wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinges remayne a long time, &amp; be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes verye ſtronge teſtimonyes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſte euerye manne. Therefore wee fynde all menne ſtriue to wright them in as good, and comely order, as poſſibly they canne. Wee ſpeake generallye euerye manne, becauſe we haue learned this in the worlde, that amonge thoſe kynde of menne, with whom the commendable exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of wrighting is moſtly, &amp; to beſt purpoſe vſed; whoſoeuer is founde to write otherwiſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> according to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty and good order, they would not haue him taken or reputed among ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt or wiſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as a man, but rather as
<pb facs="tcp:11754:6"/> a rare deformed and miſhapen mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, they thinke no greater diſcredit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> can any way fall vpon them, then to haue ſuch a one to beare the name of a companyon amyng them. But yet ful well it is knowne among many of the wyſe and learned penmen (and to wel if it might be holpen) y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> many nimble witted marchauntes (though beſydes very clowniſh &amp; dul mannered dolts) vnder the counterfect habits of graue and ciuile callynges, doe oftentymes intrude themſelues into that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable exercyſe, wyth ſuch diſhoneſt and vnſeemely behauiour, as the wiſe are no leſſe aſhamed, then grieued to thinke of that wicked abuſe, thoughe they haue not alwais power to worke redres according to their good willes. But they ſay, it is taken for a rule in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallable among them, that wit, ſubtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and wickednes: be thre ſuch louing Brothers, as ſeldome or neuer to bee founde a ſunder: and that wiſedome, pollicy, and honeſt behauioure on the other ſyde, be thre of the like. And of
<pb facs="tcp:11754:6"/> our ſelues we finde by common expe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rience, that there is no greater vvyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes in the world, then doth dailye proceede from the witty ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: and yet (beyng as blynd in wiſedome, as the man is in ſight that hath loſt both his eies) when any thing coms from him craftely and wittely deuiſed, eyther by penne or ſpeach, or any other way: he verely perſwades himſelfe, that at all handes, he is greatly extold for hys wit, but contrary to that blynde ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination of theirs, wee fynde that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the wiſe and learned, they bee had in continuall diſdayne: for they ſay, that neither wit nor learning de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerues anye reuerence at anye tyme, where honeſtye wanteth, and as for wiſedom, vvhich in the latine tongue is tearmed <hi>Sapienti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> it beareth conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually with him the ſubſtance and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uor of al goodnes, or otherwiſe it muſt looſe the name, and therefore euer to be had in great reuerence. But to bee ſhorte, beſyde all this, wee fynde by greate hunting and ſeekinge in euery
<pb facs="tcp:11754:7"/> corner, &amp; by beating in many buſhes, that there is yet an other kinde of peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple which commonly lyke hedgecre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, lye lurkinge in huggermugger, neuer once ventringe out into anye playne or open fielde, if by chaunce they come abroad they come ſo ſecret lie, as neuer ſeene eyther with pen in their eares, with bokes in their ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, or ſcarcelye with any tounge in their mouthes: if by chance they wright or ſpeake, it is alwayes in clowdes, in li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel manner, and to the defamation, &amp; diſcredite of ſome one or other par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular and ſpecial man. But theſe and all other ſortes of euill diſpoſed men, wee fynd in this worlde (the good go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment is ſuch) that continuallye they be driuen to ſilence, and that the wyſe and learned men do alwayes go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne the reſt, and be the other neuer ſo ſubtil or nimble witted, yet co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ally they do kepe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in ſubiectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; awe: and therfore thus much now we may boldlye ſay, that what ſoeuer is ſet forth by any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> either for neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes
<pb facs="tcp:11754:7"/> ſake to a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon wealth, for plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures ſake to the wryter, to gratify his friends, &amp; delight hiſelfe, or for any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reaſonable or lawful cauſe (if com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly &amp; honeſt, &amp; any thing tollerable be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſides, ſo it be not to ridiculous,) y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t wiſe &amp; beſt learned ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wil leaſt of all condemne him, but rather allowe his forward and willing mynde, for they know it is no commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thing, for euery man to be ſinguler.</p>
            <p>Conceyuing thus much, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſideatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thus had with my ſelf, I find that though in nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber the wicked &amp; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil diſpoſed men do far ſurmount the good, yet by auctority, and by good gouernment, the good doth alwayes waygh downe the apparant euils: and God forbide that any apparante wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe ſhoulde euer beare anye ſway It hath alwaies bene ſeene, that one wiſe and learned man, haue euer bene hable to kepe a thouſande other wittye naughty packes continuallye in ſubiection, and though they ſtarte out ſomtimes by ſtealth like the dod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond,
<pb facs="tcp:11754:8"/> or Snaile, yet being once but toucht, they are alwaies fayne to pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> home and ſhrinke in their Horns a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne: and God forbid, that in anye Chriſtian common wealth it ſhoulde euer be found otherwyſe. Therefore now I haue found for my purpoſe that whatſoeuer I, or any other man ſhall take vpon hym eyther to ſpeake, or wright, or any other way howſoeuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to put in acte: it is onely neceſſarilye required at euerye hande, that it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue not the iuſte rebuke or blame of the vvyſe, and honeſt diſpoſed manne: and as for thoſe which bee contrary, who feareth them, I fynde muſt feare euery blaſte of wynde: for do a manne wel, or do he ill, they will be as ready to fynd faultes, and to blame him, as the wynd wil be to blow vppon him. Wherefore now I haue taken ſuch co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage hereby, as I haue imboldned my ſelfe to fulfill the earneſt deſire of my mynde, to direct at this tyme, this litle tryfle vnto you, and if the ſmall matter herein contayned, with my
<pb facs="tcp:11754:8"/> duty and goodwill, may but deſerue to be taken in good part at your ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, wherof I nothing doubt: &amp; alſo of the wyſe, and indifferent reader, whiche hartely I doe deſyre, and lightlye to paſſe ouer ſome vayne, and vnuſuall wordes, which perhaps in diuers pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces here in may be found: then haue I obtayned the ſubſtance of my deſyre: thus leauing to imagin of, &amp; to anſwer any other obiectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s which perhappes may bee inuented agaynſt mee,) leaſt beynge to tedyous in troubli<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g you to much, I here end: and as by duty bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d duringe life to be at your commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demente, do moſt hartely commende you vnto almighty God.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From London <date>the thirde of October. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>8<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:11754:9"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11754:9"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO HIS VERY</hi> Louinge and eſpeciall <hi>friende, olde Oliuer Fyndfault, of <hi>Englande, in the countye of Europe</hi>
               </hi> Gent. William Woulwell, in moſt friendlye manner <hi>ſendeth moſt hartye greetinges.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F I ſhoulde ſo lightlye lett this paſſe, as hereby to geue fre ſcope to you my friend and to euerye o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>cleheaded penma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, (flowing by dayly practice and experience, in all cunninge, and curious conceiptes, peruſing this ſmall pamphlet, which claymeth no other tytle then a toy,) to condemne y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> inuentor hereof I ſhould great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly iniury him, and not vnworthely of greate folly might condemne my ſelf, in that I haue ſo raſhly thruſt him ſo nakedlye into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes of ſo manye, wheras perhaps if I had
<pb facs="tcp:11754:10"/> geuen him warninge thereof he might more ſtrongly and better haue furniſhed himſelfe, but as naked as I founde him, ſo nakedlye ſtrayght wayes did I prefer him. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the truth is, a very friend of myne beyng driuen from all the benefytes and pleaſures of this world, and inforced contrarye to the ordinances and rules of nature to hyde and harbor himſelf (though as a gu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ltles gueſt) in a moſt ſolitary and dumpiſh deſert, beyng therwith drawen from all ioy and felicity, in in any worldly neceſſary practiſe, and rather indeuoring himſelfe to recreate, refreſh, and delight his mind with ſome toy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſh conceipts, then otherwiſe (being ſo inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bred) to charge it with any matters of importance or weight for his owne ſolace and pleaſure, beſtowed ſome part of that his ydle tyme in certayne playne and light toyes of inuentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, not much vnlike therein vnto a certayne ydle kinge in <hi>Perſia,</hi> who in his progreſſes, did nothig els but continuallye cutt, and whittle ſtickes, to dryue awaye the tyme. And by reaſon of my dayly recourſe vnto him, beyng priuye ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto, I craued and obtayned the coppye of this now extant, the which I diuers times and ofte peruſynge ouer, toke occaſion as a toy, to lyke ſo well, as I procurde it to the preſſe, with this title as you ſee, and thought it as a toke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> worthy to ſend vnto you, to read
<pb facs="tcp:11754:10"/> whether beyng led there unto, by the greate &amp; good affection I bare to the maker, or by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſart of the matter, I know not: but wel wee both know, it is the naturall incliation of friendes, one alwayes to thinke the beſt of an other. Therefore as I know the firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentor hereof ment nothing leſſe, then to put this forth to the publicke conſtruction of the world, to haſarde or aduenture the allowing or diſalowing therof: I wil not take vponme to geue out any ſhowe of commendatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in at all. Fyrſt becauſe I knowe it was not made to that intente, and beſydes, leaſt if it ſhould happen to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dempned of others as a vayne and tryfling toy, I ſhould therewith alſo be condempned to haue made a partiall and vnworthye prayſe. But ſyr (if you can rightly conſider it) as by the leaſt byrde that flyes in the ayre, by the leaſt fiſh that ſwims in the Sea, and by the ſmalleſt worme that creepes vpon the earth. The omnipotent &amp; mighty power of God doth as fully &amp; playne appeare, as by the hougeſt and greateſt mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters that beares life in this worlde: euen ſo by the ſmaleſt booke that can be written, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt babling ballet that can be made, and by the leaſt word that can be ſpoken, his ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge and wonderful workes in ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, with his moſt liberall and incomparable guiftes vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:11754:11"/> do as perfectly ſet forth and ſhew themſelues as by the greateſt volume y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euer was writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, by the wayghtyeſt or wyſeſt concept that euer was made, or by the moſt eloquente or learned oration that euer was vttered. The honeſt wyſe and ciuil man doth as little deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyſe the worſt and meaneſt begger that goeth by the waye, as he geeatly honoureth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt &amp; greateſt prince that ruleth in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world, euen ſo here the indifferent and wel diſpoſed myndes, wil as litle trippe, or ſpu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne at thys ſtumped, lame, and haui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nge toy, as they would greatly fawne vppon, or runne after a more fyne or pleaſaunt inuention. But ther is an old prouerb <hi>Figulus Figulo inuidit,</hi> one Potter hateth an other, the which to auoyd, theſe may be ſufficiently to aſſure you, in that I know you are a craftes man in that arte, that as for this vnſkilful potter, this ſmall trifle and toy is the firſt that euer hee made, who wil not iuſtify it to be lawful nor good, in that he was neuer prentice thereunto, and for any he intendes, I dare bouldly ſay ſhall be the laſt, vnleſſe it be a little cup or crueſe for his owne mouth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yet ſyr if your friendly actions hadde at anye tyme bene<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> agreable vnto your continual colourable ſhowes, you would haue inabled him long before this by your friendly inſtructions, worthye of your felowſhip and company.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:11754:11"/>
            <p>But vnderſtanding he had, though to verye ſmall and litle purpoſe, ſome ſmacke in this your art, as only to take your veſſels in hand and to reade them ouer, you alwayes ſhooke hym of, demaunding a double fee for the tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chinge of your ſkill, much like to amuſition, who vſed to take of hysſchollare, which had learned before they came vnto him, double ſoulare, deuble that he toke of others, which neuer learned before, ſayinge that hee tooke double paynes with them, as fyrſt to make them forget that they had learned before, and then to teach them perfectlye agayne: who if now he were alyue ſhoulde ſurelye fynde as ſmall reſorte of ſchollers, as I thinke you do in that you are ſo curyous in your art. Ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore to imagine this ſhort, and vnpleaſaunte ſounde, here at this tyme preſented vnto your audable and pleaſaunt eares, to be but as a preludium, vnto other conceytes, &amp; that he wil ſtryue to marre your markets, with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuch lyke rough hewen, or miſhapen veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, it ſhal be in vayn, for be intendes nothig leſſe. And as for this ſmall conceipt, here at this tyme, being caſt in a very litle mould, &amp; wherin great want of an artifitial workman muſt needes appeare: I hope you will not ſtryue to condemne, but rather excuſe, though it hath neyther heade to begynne, handle to houlde by, nor foote to ſtand vpon &amp; though
<pb facs="tcp:11754:12"/> perhaps neare aboute the end you ſhall find it very imperfect, and ſo ful of ſecrete chinks and litle crantſe, as it wil hardly hold liquor without leaking: but if your graue head ſhal eſteeme it as an ydle toy, imagine it (as it is) the fruictes of an ydle place. For phiſicke ſake I know you haue ſwallowed many vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſant and bitter pylles, for friendſhip ſake you may as wel at this time digeſt this tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fling and ydle toy. But if you ſhal anſweare mee, that your ſuch Phiſical reſcerpts haue alwaies inforced you to vſe the pap of an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, or els to roule them in ſuger, otherwiſe they might haue ſtucke in your throate: then for anſweare agayne, I can but aduiſe you, for the more eaſy digeſting of this my friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conceipt, ſent onely as a token vnto you &amp; to the reſt of my friendes, to roule it in ſtyd of an apple, in the ſott asd ſlyppery pappe of your gentle pattence, or otherwyſe (in ſtead of a ſuger lofe) in ſome ſweete and ſugred ſpice of your moſt frienly interpretation: and in this (for the old acquayntaunce of longe tyme continued betweene vs) I hope I ſhal not fayle but miſſe of your willing &amp; friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conformity: and therfore now, ſince I haue ſufficiently declared vnto you, the cauſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> publiſhing herof, with the diſpoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of the deuiſor, and leaſt I ſhoulde make this my foretrotti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ſhew or preamble (which
<pb facs="tcp:11754:12"/> rightly ſhould be but a breefe declaration of what is to come) longer then this his whole raſe which is very ſhort, and conſideryng my old leſſon (worthy in euery act to be remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred and obſerued) <hi>quod ſatis eſt ſufficit,</hi> I commend me vnto you, you vnto God, and theſe few lines following vnto your friendly conſtruction.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your aſſured friend VVilliam VVouldwell.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:11754:13"/>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>A SHORT PRELVDIVM to the friendly Reader.</head>
               <q>Interpone tuis interdum ga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dia curis</q>
               <lg>
                  <l>TO mingle mirth ſometymes vvith care</l>
                  <l>and vſyng neither of them to much</l>
                  <l>Preſerues thy body vvel in health,</l>
                  <l>it keepes thy mynd in perfect ſtate.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>To glutte in ſorrovv day and night</l>
                  <l>from day to day, from yeare to yeare,</l>
                  <l>Thou drovvnſt thy ſelfe in drouſy moodes,</l>
                  <l>it ſyngles thee from all thy vvites</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The hotchpot for varietyes ſake</l>
                  <l>is oft accepted of the beſt</l>
                  <l>And taken as a daynty diſh</l>
                  <l>if kyndly mixt vvith diuers taſtes</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Reſceites of all preſeruatiues</l>
                  <l>vvhere ſhall you fynde more fyt for health</l>
                  <l>Then vvher the ſkilful mixtures be</l>
                  <l>in dayly practiſe to be made.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>A ſugred ſvveete and ſyluer ſound</l>
                  <l>the muſicke mixt doth alvvayes yeeld</l>
                  <l>VVith harmony ſo heauenly,</l>
                  <l>vvherein no man but greatly ioyes.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And here to make a vvindovv fight,</l>
                  <l>out of my mynd, novv to your eyes</l>
                  <l>Since mixtures make all thinges ſo good,</l>
                  <l>let this my hotchpot beare no blame.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:11754:13"/>
                  <l>A flickeryng flye vvith fettered fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ete,</l>
                  <l>faſt tyde in ſcrauling Spyders vveb,</l>
                  <l>A ſtinking ſeate of flattering Fleete,</l>
                  <l>vvhere <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>arſe he can put out his nebb.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>A byrde, a beaſt, more meeter may</l>
                  <l>the vvitles vvoodcock paynt himſelfe</l>
                  <l>VVhom beaten ſeamen did aſſaye,</l>
                  <l>ſo oft to vvarne from ſhollovv ſhelfe,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>A guiltles gueſt and harbored longe</l>
                  <l>in hollovv caue of hardeſt ſtone,</l>
                  <l>VVith patience novv doth ſalue his vvronge.</l>
                  <l>and vviſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> it vvere his harme alone,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>From thence this ydle toy doth ſpring</l>
                  <l>vvher vvere greene nimble vvitſeed ſovvn</l>
                  <l>Greate crops of toyes that field might b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ing,</l>
                  <l>and ranke, if oft it vvere not movvne.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>VVe ſee vvhen grovvnd is nevvly layed,</l>
                  <l>vvith vveedes and thiſtles fyrſt it ſpringes,</l>
                  <l>VVhen ſutes in loue be fyrſt aſſayd,</l>
                  <l>it fyrſt vvith triflyng toyes begynnes,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Before vvee come to mannes eſtate,</l>
                  <l>in childiſh toyes longe tyme vve ſpend</l>
                  <l>And after then our youthul rate,</l>
                  <l>vve vvalke as vvild til nere our ende.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11754:14"/>
                  <l>VVho vvil ſtrong houldes attempt to vvin,</l>
                  <l>do firſt vvith vveaklinges trye their ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth,</l>
                  <l>And ſo the ſtrykers all begin</l>
                  <l>and grovv to courage great at length.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Before the ſouldiour preſſe to vvarres</l>
                  <l>he muſters fyrſt in ſport to trye</l>
                  <l>And there if fit, the boulder dares</l>
                  <l>aduenture then in field to dye.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>VVe likevviſe ſee vvhen plants do ſpring,</l>
                  <l>before their leaues can ſpread abrode,</l>
                  <l>Firſt forth their litle buds muſt bring,</l>
                  <l>and then at length their bovves they lode,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thus euery thing if rightly vvayde,</l>
                  <l>vvith tryfles ſmall doth fyrſt begin</l>
                  <l>Rightly therfore it is not ſayd,</l>
                  <l>this tryfling toy great blame doth vvinne.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>A needful thing in common vvealth</l>
                  <l>no man, nor vvoman thinkes to long.</l>
                  <l>VVhich ſoule or body bringes to health</l>
                  <l>but ſtill more more is all their ſong</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>A tryfling toy in priuate ſporte</l>
                  <l>if tedious vvorkes vvithout delight,</l>
                  <l>Blame not therfore this ioy though ſhort</l>
                  <l>vvhich needles here is brought to light.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <pb n="2" facs="tcp:11754:14"/>
                     <head>Patet que pardit virtutis arctaque via eſt.</head>
                     <p>The Caſtle</p>
                     <p>This nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row lane of virtue with her 4 capt.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Prudence<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Iuſtice. Fortitude Tempera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>reſceyues to reſt.</p>
                     <p>of reſt</p>
                     <p>this wide field with theſe 3 captaynes</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> world. The fleſh. The Deuil</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Leades al to diſtru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
                     <p>The vvorldly ſouldiours.</p>
                     <figDesc>diagram of castle</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:11754:15"/>
               <p>THe godly, polliticke, &amp; wiſe gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the one, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the wicked, ſubtil, &amp; diuiliſh illutions of the other, euer ſince their beginning &amp; firſt entring into field of worldly fight, which was when Adam at the firſt ſubtle intiſement, &amp; temptinge tounge of <hi>Eue,</hi> fyrſt puld the Apple of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tree, is by many learned and godlye auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors far mor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> aptly diſcribed, better ſet forth, more largelye &amp; playnly publyſhed then poſſibly by anye here at this tyme, can be ſpoken or imagined.</p>
               <p>And the lyke I may ſay of euerye other particular theame, in this ſhorte, &amp; ſmall pamphlet hereafter following.</p>
               <p>For euery litle ſtrayte and norrowe path which here is taken woulde moſt eaſilye conduct and playnly lead a moſt cunning and perfite penman into a moſte ample, and large field moſt pleaſant and neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</p>
               <p>And therefore leauinge that wyde and fertil field wherin moſt ſweete, holeſom, and neceſſarye flowers of greate good, and requiſite matters might bee gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red (as to intreate now at this preſent of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:11754:15"/> theſe three vyſes and fower virtues, with the ſubſtance of euery other mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter hereafter followinge,) I rather bende my iourney forthwith according to the tytle of this toy, into a more ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crete and ſyldome uſed garden, where I intende not to gather of all ſortes of flowers ſuch plenty as to make therof a great and goodly garland, but rather more likely no flower of pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ure at al. For wel do I know, that hardly ſhould I finde (were I in place neuer ſo plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull) ſuch a flower of pleaſure or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyght, which hath not alreadye hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, by ſome or other bene preſented vnto many tender noſes, who perhaps if agayne they ſhould be tryed with the lyke, would rather ſtop their noſes, &amp; diſalow therof, beyng ſo oft cloyde with ſuch accuſtomed ſauors, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they would prayſe the ſweetnes thereof were it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo pleaſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, which we dayly ſee by great experience, as for example this for one amonge many others may well bee noted, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> when wanton youth moſt
<pb facs="tcp:11754:16"/> wyldlye flyinge here and there exercy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the youthful winges of his vncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant and flickeringe mynd, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> place to place, light happily vpon ſome fertile, and pleaſaunt ground, where he fynds great plentye of ſweete and comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble flowers: then ſettelynge his mynde according to the humour of his eye, hee ſyts him downe as it were vppon ſome one choiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> ſpetial moulehil neere vnto to the flower he beſt delytes: and there reſting his bodye from tyme to tyme, (though with a reſtles mynde) rather willing to feede the deſire of his wanto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eye. in ſtil peruſing &amp; beholding his cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen &amp; long eye bitten flower, then to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfy his hungry and needy ſtomacke, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> any other nouriſhing or neceſſary food: at length after many baſhful, &amp; priuate attemptes, ſometyme handling y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtalk &amp; oftentymes kiſſing the leaues: gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring vp ſome crummes of courage, ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daynly takes it vp by the rootes, &amp; ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes it cleane awaye: which lightly hee kepes for a tyme moſt louingly, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>while in his hand, ſomewhile in his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:11754:16"/> and ſtrayght in his lap, ſomtyme to his noſe, ſome tyme to his lips, &amp; not vnlike but ſomtyme to his bed: for that he wakes no ſoner in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> morning then he deſyres to haue it neere his noſe, to bee ſhort, his delightes be ſuch therein, as who knows not that he eſteemes it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all other growinge herbes, or flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers vnder the ſunne: he loues it accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the old ſaying of the poet <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creon,</hi> as a ſweete miſchiefe, and with the ſaying of <hi>Propertius,</hi> as a ſweete ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny becauſe he indureth his torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts willingly, &amp; is ſildome content to ſettle or quiet his mynde where he lyues, but alwayes there where hee loues. Hee ſtickes not for the loue thereof to adue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture the ouerthrow of his owne body w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Roderick</hi> of Spaine, who loſt his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome for the loue of <hi>Camma:</hi> or to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſe the deathe and deſtruction of a ſtraunger, with <hi>Retormodicus,</hi> who o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrewe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole ſtate of the <hi>Lacede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monians</hi> for the loue of <hi>Scedaſus</hi> daugh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ters, &amp; w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Cateline,</hi> who ſlue his owne ſonne for the loue of <hi>Oreſtilla.</hi> And all this not withſtandinge, after a whyle,
<pb facs="tcp:11754:17"/> his eager ſight beyng once ſatiſfyed, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the reſt of his ſenſes which before toke their delightes: grow as greate to mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlikingr as before in theire firſt begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning they kyndled and grew to loue, a thing no leſſe ſtraunge vnto all ſuch as ſtil remayne free their flower to choſe, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it were miraculous for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hot mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t <hi>Aetna,</hi> to become the cold hil <hi>Caucaſus,</hi> &amp; whoſe lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſoeuer, it is to tread y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world do not vnlikely ſtu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble oftentymes vpon many ſuch (though loſt and caſt away) pleaſant and ſweete flowers. This ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample the worlde ouer is dayly ſeene. And therefore now, ſince that ſuch fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous inuentions be ſo cunningly deuy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and ſeuerallye knyt vp togeather, you may for a pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny haue in your pocket choyſe of many prety toyes at al times to delight you. I know it were now in vayne for me to ſtriue to gather y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> like, though my inforced ydle leaſure might wel ſerue theru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to, for in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it ſhould be ſuperfluous, it woulde rather greatly yr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any thing at al delight: but my
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:11754:17"/> intent is (though I bee longe in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming therto) in this my choſen and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary Garden, to pick out y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flyng and vayneſt weedes that poſſiblye may be fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, and therwith to make (to paſſe my weary tyme) a ſmall and litle poeſy, the rather for that I know, many be ſo cloyde with pleaſaunt and ſweete ſauors, as they oftentymes ſeeke for moſt filthy and ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inking weedes to ſinel vpon. But as I woulde not ſtryue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yonde my ſkill to pricke this ful of ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſaunt and delectable flowers, euen ſo would I be loth to poyſon it with ſuch vnholeſome and ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inking weedes as it ſhould yeeld too fylthy or yrkſome a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour. Therfore if I be not deceyued, it ſhal yeeld very barely any ſauor eyther ſweete or lower at all: and in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o doinge as the ſweetenes ſhal litle delite you, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſower taſt ſhall as little offende you. And therfore to be ſhort, leauing theſe circumſtaunces and endles rownd run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning about the buſh. The firſt begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning hereof (though more brieflye then cunningly) ſhowes the weake and f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ble
<pb facs="tcp:11754:18"/> entring of man firſt into this wicked worlde nouriſhed vp, and ſafelye kept by three choſen nurſes (though in more ſoft and gentle bandes) not much vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like to the pore captiues and priſoners vnder the cuſtody and chaynes of theire appoynted gaylors, vntill the Seſſion dai of their gail deliuery: wher ſtraight they reſeaue their iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts (as by the law rightly condempned) to bee led into the wyde wildernes of this wretched world, wher (as pilgrims) paſſyng lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g youthful and wearye tyme, ſome lyght happely into the hands of good &amp; God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſpoſed men, ſome into the hands of moſt cruel tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, whoſe ſimple, ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>celes &amp; bru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſh mynds ſerue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually to torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and deſtroy y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> next vnarmed na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weake men, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> by chaunce fall into their deuiliſh dints, in reue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge of ſome iniury done vnto them before theyr equals, or ſuperiours: from the which I pray god deliuer me, &amp; preſerue al others. Some agayne are choſen and placed in princely ſeat of rule: ſome in place of diuine cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, ſome in place to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ouriſh and ſeede
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:11754:18"/> a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon wealth, ſome to cure the ſick, and diſeaſed bodies, and ſome continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in place to deceaue the whole world with whom no ſticklers at any time, as yet coulde euer preuale, til death him ſelfe in proper perſon, coms to play his moſt playne and vnſkilfull quarters, as hereafter in this ſmall Pamp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er, doth more playnly &amp; briefely appere, a thing though vnfi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly intermingled with ſuch idle and vayne inuentions, and though vnaptly bearyng the title aboue named in that the name of god ought neuer to be ſo taken in vayne as once to bee na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med vnder the title of ſuch a toy: yet my intent, and matter therin conſidered, it ſhall not bee greatlye amis, if by the reader it may be conſtrued to the beſt: (which I deſire) for I ſtryue not to iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtefy the perfectnes therof, informe, in ſtyle, in matter, or in any thyng. And therefore I may not otherwiſe but co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend it (as a tryling <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oy) vnno the beſt and moſt friendly conſtruction.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:11754:19"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>THe ſilly babe in cradel rockt</l>
                  <l>cries alvvaies out as pincht vvith paines</l>
                  <l>That impiſh thing, it vvould be knockt</l>
                  <l>ſayth hairbraind hag, knock out the brains.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But ſhee ful little knovves or thinks</l>
                  <l>Of cradle crying miſtery</l>
                  <l>VVhere man to death his draft firſt drinkes,</l>
                  <l>And there lith cheaud to miſery.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>It ſpeakes a language ſtrange to man,</l>
                  <l>vvhich fevv or none vvel vnderſtandes</l>
                  <l>But fayne it vvould from vvhence it came,</l>
                  <l>to earth agayne from all thoſe bandes,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>It ſtrugles vveakly God doth knovv</l>
                  <l>Ful oft vvithin the Nurce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> armes,</l>
                  <l>Then geue it leaue the mynd to ſhovv,</l>
                  <l>to earth it flyes and feares no harmes.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But vvhat ſhould cauſe ſuch harmeles ſoules</l>
                  <l>to ſtriue ſo ſtrangely ſtraight to dye.</l>
                  <l>It is a ball vvhich nature trovvles</l>
                  <l>Before their eies, though ſecretle.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Of glaſſe, vvherin they ſee their vvoes</l>
                  <l>vvhich in this vvorld they muſt abyde</l>
                  <l>And that they be among their foes,</l>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:11754:19"/>
                  <l>And therfore they vvould gladly hyde.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But ſtriue or ſtrougle as they vvill,</l>
                  <l>vvrith or vvreſt vvhich vvay they can.</l>
                  <l>And cry or bleare they out their fill</l>
                  <l>they lye ſtil tyde til ſtate of man.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And then as ſone as they begin</l>
                  <l>to grovve in ſtrength to treade the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d,</l>
                  <l>The Father captayne ſtryues to vvin.</l>
                  <l>and trayne them by alluring ſound.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Straight from their babiſh ſvvadling bandes,</l>
                  <l>into the ample fighting field,</l>
                  <l>And firſt geue them into their handes</l>
                  <l>their Abſey bookes, as ſpeare and ſhield.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>VVhervvith vve dayly ſee them vvalke,</l>
                  <l>and toſſing them (though childiſhly)</l>
                  <l>As ſilly tatling babes in talke,</l>
                  <l>not thinking of their miſery.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And hovv they all be preſt to fight</l>
                  <l>in field of vvorldly vvretched vvoe,</l>
                  <l>But vvantonnes is their delite</l>
                  <l>Till they to vvretched field do goe,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>VVherin all fathers do agree.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11754:20"/>
                  <l>As captaynes tryde in vvarres before</l>
                  <l>And longes in armes the childe to ſee</l>
                  <l>vvhich doth great ioyes to them reſtore,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And thus mans lyfe is militant</l>
                  <l>in dayly ſtyrring here and there:</l>
                  <l>Of courage ſtoute and puiſſaunt.</l>
                  <l>before all thinges that earth doth beare.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>From cruel vvarres it neuer ſtint,</l>
                  <l>though bloudſhed ſmall or none be ſeene,</l>
                  <l>A thouſand tymes more hard then flint,</l>
                  <l>a fort it doth beſiege to vvin,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>VVhich vvorldly art did neuer make</l>
                  <l>nor can be vvon, but by the beſt</l>
                  <l>And named, (vvhich force can neuer ſhake)</l>
                  <l>the ſeate of euerlaſting reſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>VVho thinkes his life moſt ſtrong to fight</l>
                  <l>agaynſt the vvorld<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> his raſe to end.</l>
                  <l>Is ſoneſt brought to vvofull plight</l>
                  <l>if vertue doth no ſuccour ſend.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Nd therfore the neceſſary &amp; wayghty force hereof conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, who could moſt cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly or cloſly conuay him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe into the ſight of this moſt cruell &amp;
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:11754:20"/> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinual battaile) bearyng alwaies be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his body, true faith, as his buckler, &amp; placing conſtancy as a ſure bulwarke of defence, ſhould doobtles daily behold far more wonderful wracke, &amp; deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, with more ſecrete ſubtil pollicies &amp; deceiptes, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> through y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole world in any our accuſtomed bloudy conflicts, betwixt man &amp; ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, he could poſſibly ſee al dayes of his life. No blowes be ther to be ſeene, no noyſe to be hard, no vau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of victory at any tyme to bee made, the ſlaughter be it neuer ſo great, is euer ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and ſcile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Al deadly wounds being there daily and howerly infinite and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable one only Phiſition doth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes cure, who farre beyond all art, doth ſo continually ſtrengthen and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh all thoſe inca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ped and fightynge ſouldiers, as from the tyme they firſt pitched their field vnto this day the bat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tayle neuer quailde, nor yet till the laſt hower euer ſhall. But now beyng out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward (as an vnſkilfull paſſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger of this my ſhorte and eaſye iourneye, yf I ſhould contrary to my farmer promiſe,
<pb facs="tcp:11754:21"/> forſake my playne and eaſy trot, and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly fal into a more ſwift, and curious pace, intending to leape and runne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond my limits into this wyde fielde, &amp; world of continuall warre. Uppon my returne agayne, you woulde certaynly expect a perfect &amp; true report of ſome great and wonderful newes, the order and manner of their field, with diſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſome notable late battaile, and conqueſt, with many other queſtions, which (for want of experience) I ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not imagine: and then if my iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, eloquence, and memorye (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he chiefeſt tooles, and inſtruments of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry cunning and perfect wiſe meſſenger) being tried with the touchſtone of ſome artificiall workeman: ſhall appeare ſo vtterlye voyde of anye good, or perfite mettall, as in no parte able to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fourme what is loked for, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſhall iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be condempned, in ſo fooliſhly diſclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing mine owne im<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ecility &amp; weaknes: which otherwiſe by ſcile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce I might ſtil haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cealed. Therfore I wil not take vpon me as a meſſenger of any ſkill, to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:11754:21"/> make any report therof. But whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer can wyſely and wel diſpoſe himſelf ſhal more fitly be his owne meſſenger. And ther may behold the innumerable number of worldlinges, hauinge conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually their deſyred fort in view, dayly marching forward therunto, howe by many ſubtill and ſecrete pollicyes they they be alwayes foreſtald, &amp; ſtopt theyr waye, and ſhall playnly ſee, agaynſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerye lone and ſingle man, thre moſt ſtronge and mightye aduerſaryes, the world, the fleſh, and the deuil, who co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually keepe themſelues moſt ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in armes, hauinge wonne y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rule and dominion of the greateſt parte of the worlde, onely leauing a moſt narrow &amp; ſtraight lane vnto this our fort and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle of reſt, wherin ſtandes Vertue, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng at continuall warre and defiance a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thoſe deadly and mortal enemies of man, as ſtrongly and as ſurelye fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed againſt them, as poſſiblye may be. With continuall becks and ſignes: not fayling dayly and howerly to ſende her ſecrete priuy ſcoutes, and meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers
<pb facs="tcp:11754:22"/> from man to man, to inſtructe and geue vs knowledge of that narrowe and ſecret way, and therwith neuer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſeth, to ſuch as be willing to followe her to accompany and aſſiſt them, with what ſtrength ſhe can poſſibly make<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to ſafecanduite and leade them through y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thickeſt of theire ennemyes. But this vertue (beynge a continuall and open fiend vnto vs) with all her moſt &amp; ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt furniture of munition and defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, is dayly met withall, and incountered and yet ſtrongly abides thoſe continual conflictes, ſometyme eſcaping with vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorye, and ſometyme with loſſe: but moſt ſyldome doth ſhe returne conque<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red vnleſſe the diſſemblinge Captiue (whom her purpoſe is to ſafecunduit &amp; defende) moſt cowardlye quayles, and ſhrynkes from her by the way.</p>
               <p>The pore ſouldiour, is no ſoner eſpyed by his diligent dayly attendantes, the world, the fleſh, and the deuil, to be cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aping a way vnder the ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner of vertue, but ſtrayghte they flye vnto him with as ſure hold as poſſible may be, &amp; then
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:11754:22"/> beyng faynt harted, eaſy to be aſſured, by their glorious and ſubtill outwarde ſhowes of deceyt, hee eaſily lets goe his hould by vertue, and yeeldes to their ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ous (though ſecrete) fleſhly, &amp; car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall tugges. But contrariwyſe if he be ſo ſtrong of courage not eaſy to be cari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by any ſecrete or ſubtil whyrl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wynde, or ſo wary in wiſdome and foreſight, as to eſchew all their forewarned ſnares, and willing to withſtand thoſe his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemyes vnto death, then ſhee moſt lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uingly, and readily imbraceth hym, as her adopted child: and then to beholde how gently and eaſily ſhe lyke a natural mother, drawes hym by little and little, out of the tearynge Teeth of thoſe moſt cruell tyrantes, and how cunningly and carefully ſhee ſtriues to cary him ſafely throughe their daungerous and cruell force, it woulde doubtles dryue all her ſtrongeſt ennemies moſt earneſtlye and faythfully to loue, honor, and obay her, euen to the end.</p>
               <p>And thus in vewynge the ſecret and cunning warres be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>twixt the world and
<pb facs="tcp:11754:23"/> this our mortall life, (wherein much more may bee vnderſtode, then by this ydle pen, can poſſibly bee vttered) our ſubtill and ſecrete ennemyes wee ſhall the better eſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hew, and our ſafeſt way to the caſtell and ſeate of euerlaſting reſt, ſhall more eaſilye learne, which (as ſeemes is not the broade and common beaten way, but rather a very narrow and ſildome troden moſſey lane. And as our foreſayde aduerſaries with al their armye, and might be dayly remayning in the one, geuinge vs continuall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulce in all attemptes vnto this our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting fort: and trayninge vs lyke dronken myſe into theire flatterynge pytfalles of euerlaſtinge deſtruction: Euen ſo our moſt louing and naturall friend vertue. with al her power conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually poſſeſſeth the other (which is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> narrow lane) alwayes readye on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſyde, there to reſceaue vs in. And theruppon is it written, though other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe. as wel it may be vnderſtood)</p>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>Patet quae perdit. &amp;c.</q>
               </epigraph>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:11754:23"/>
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> The friendly <hi>gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and comminge togeather</hi> betwene Idlenes, &amp; <hi>a ſtudent.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He godly &amp; wel diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed man, ſatlinge<note place="margin">Student.</note> hymſelfe both in bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and mynd, (bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng as faythfully the knees of his hart, as many do faynedly in moſt diſſemblynge manner the knees of their outward bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes) vnto his deuoute meditations, &amp; prayers, is very ſenſably to his feeling as he certaynlye thinkes, pulled often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times by the head oft times by the legg<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ſome tyme by other parts of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. It is not a thinge ſtrange or rare to be heard of, that moſt ſtraunge &amp; terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble viſions haue alſo appered vnto ſuch kynd of men, to moue them vnto terror and feare of purpoſe to remoue them from their ſuch deuotion and prayer: who it is, or what it is, that doth worke
<pb facs="tcp:11754:24"/> and bryng ſuch continual lettes, and i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbraunces vnto them, I leaue to the graue and learned deuynes, whoſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion (for want of knowledge) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther dare, nor can take vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me to ſhew: yet for my playne and ſhort opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, I thinke it is the ſecrete ſnatching, and priuy byting degge of hel.</p>
               <p>But the godly and holy men are ſo day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly &amp; hourly bitt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n therwith, as come y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuil himſelfe, his dog, or his damme, or what ſaynt ſoeuer of his hee liſtes to ſende, the ofter they fele themſelues bit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten, and ſnatcht at, the ofter and more greatly do they take occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therby, not onely to pray the more deuowtly, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo more hartelye to reioyce vnto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, knowing that the deuil, with al hys companye of Angelles, is neuer ſo diligent and eager in buſyinge himſelfe to winne, but where he lighteth in ſuch running company of gamſters, as he is alwayes in feare to looſe, which ys ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer among dyſers, and carders, nor yet in any alchouſe, or ryplynge paſtymes,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:11754:24"/> neuer in any feaſting, or banketinge, nor in braue and gorgious ſhowes, nor yet in any one delyght, or worldly pleaſure at al, for in ſome of theſe, as in continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all dyſing and cardinge, which is neuer without ſwearyng and ſtaring, in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall feaſting and banketting whiche is neuer without dronkennes, and glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tony with ſuch lyke, he is neuer in fear among the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as once to looſe. But which of them ſoeuer can beſt and moſt clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beare his ale, or with hys cunninge ſlaightes and ingling trickes, deceaue moſt, and win of all the reſt. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he denill for his part is ſure at the end as cleanly to beare him, and as cunninglye to win them all, and as in worldly delytes hee lykewyſe reſteth hymſelfe quiet, neuer offering any trouble or diſquiet vnto a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them, onely in hope that the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of the world wil be ſufficient in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumentes to drawe them alſo to the bente of hys bowe, as well as if he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe were in preſence among them: &amp; this appeiſeth his bottomles and inſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiable gulph,
<pb facs="tcp:11754:25"/> deſyrous if poſſibly he might to drown and draw vnto himſelfe, the pore inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centes and ſoules of al the worlde. But there be many godly and well diſpoſed men, who by the continuall helpe, and inſpiration of the holy Ghoſt, haue at all attemptes as great cunninge to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent hym, as he hath alwayes ſubtillye in ſeeking to tempte and deceaue them: they neuer muſe or ſtart at anye of hys ſodayne or ſecrete ſhadowes, but conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuallye laboure and bend themſeues to withſtand his ſuch wicked deuiſes.</p>
               <p>And now to ſhew my preſent and ſecret trouble, euen ſo in the verye ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, though not ſetling my ſelfe in the lyke Godlineſſe of deuotion, as before mentioned, yet bendyng my ſelfe vnto a worldly and neceſſary ſtudye, I feele e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen now of late very cenſably &amp; playnly many ſecret and priuy twitches, but by whom I cannot imagine (hearing nor ſeyng any thing at all,) as for the deuil I hope it is not, for man or woman it cannot poſſibly be: and therfore (deſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to follow as nere as I canne, the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:11754:25"/> ſteppes of theſe godly, and well diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,) what ſoeuer it is, vntil I hear further therof, I wil not ſo eaſily be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercome.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Idlenes.</head>
                  <p>Sir to driue you from your dumps and great admirations, it is euen I.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Studient.</head>
                  <p>Friend Idlenes, I may not ſay wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come. But ſince you are come, geue me your hande: what was the cauſe, that you ſo oft &amp; ſo ſecretly puld m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e by the ſleeue, that I could neuer neither ſee, nor heare you?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Idlenes.</head>
                  <p>Oh ſyr, it was for verye mere good will which I did beare, as alwayes I haue borne moſt willingly vnto you.</p>
                  <p>For loking priuely and peping ouer your ſhoulders, and ſeynge you ſo ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly
<pb facs="tcp:11754:26"/> beſyde your booke. I thought w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> my ſelfe, if ſodaynlye I ſhoulde haue blowen out my trumpet, or haue brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed any loude ſounde, or ſynging into your eares, or if ſodainly I ſhould haue appeared vnto you, I mighte perhaps haue ſo frighted, and driuen you vnto ſuch a ſodayne ſtart and terrible feare, as durynge your lyfe euer after, you mighte thereby haue fallen into ſome wonderful and great paulſey: and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the moſt gentle and fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner I coulde, I eaſily and priuily (fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring your ſuch diſturbance) puld you by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſleeue: Whereupon hearynge you ſo grauely beginning your grounde, and running ſuch deſcant vpon the Deuill, hys dogge, and his damme, I ſtoode a longe tyme (as though greatle ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed) expectinge your laſte ſtroke, and how you would make your cloſe: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by at length, I might plainly perceyue you in a manner likened mee (though not named) vnto the Deuill and hys dogge, which (conſideryng my continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:11754:26"/> friendlye mynde towardes you) I could not chuſe, but take very vnkynd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Student.</head>
                  <p>Friend iniury, I knowe you haue not bene ſo baſelye brought vp in beggers boſome with ignoraunce, but that you do as well know the order and courſe of this worlde, as the greatteſt learned, &amp; moſt famous Clarke of all: your white heade, and many yeares in greate expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience haue brought you ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, to counteruayle the beſt: conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall companye and oft handlynge doe bryng the wyld and brutiſh beaſtes, at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> length to be tame: and manye Byrdes, as Parattes, and Pyes, with ſuch lyke oftentymes to ſpeake. Experience tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth vs, that companye many tymes doth worke greate wonders: and what is it that company will not cauſe, The old Prouerbe is, that companye often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tymes doth make many olde men verye good cookes: and my frend take you fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <pb facs="tcp:11754:27"/> company take your heade from your ſhoulders. Somtyme like a roge, and ſhakeragge, halfe naked, a man may fynd you dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cing among beggers, ſome while brawling, and fighting, and ſome time cracking of lice, ſomtime in mean apparaile, in tauernes, and tipling hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, toſſing, and ſwilling, and cracking of crownes, ſometyme agayne, in moſt braue and gorgious attyre, a companio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with the beſt: to be ſhort, of what eſtate or calling is he of, into whoſe company ſometyme or other, you haue not intru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded your ſelfe.</p>
                  <p>Therfore beyng ſo well acqnaynted, as I know you are with the natures, and diſpoſitions of all men, it ſemeth verye ſtraunge vnto me, that now you ſhoulde ſeeme ſo ignorant of me, as to take anye thing vnkindly whatſoener I haue ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of you: for you know right wel, that notwithſtanding moſt men are content ſecretly oftentymes to entertayne you, yet few or none at any tyme, but roges and knaues, dare for their credits ſake, openly allow or commend you: it can not
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:11754:27"/> bee alſo vnknowen vnto you, that you haue alwayes bene cronacled to be y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor and mother of all miſchiefe &amp; vice, calling your wits togeather, and reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring your ſelfe, you know more herein the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I can tel you. Therfore neuer take the wordes of your friende, when they ſeeme to offende you, but rather hys mind. For notwithſtanding my former ſpeech I wil not be to curious, nor ſhye of your company, a wyſe ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (I know) ſometyme wil admit of the ſimple foole and prating knaue to ſit at hys bord, the one to make ſport in laughing, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other in talkinge, and both to paſſe away the tyme: for a yonge man to bee alwayes graue, vntil his very roote beginnes, &amp; growes to bee gray: were ſurely in my concept as greate a follye in hym, as if alwayes he ſhould be ydle. Therfore my friend, ſince now you haue ſo gently, ſo aduyſedly, and ſo friendly preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted your ſelfe vnto me, and beynge I knowe the meſſenger and ſeruante, and atturney of an atturney, diſcourage not your ſelfe at any thing I haue ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but euen as
<pb facs="tcp:11754:28"/> bould as you would be with the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt acquaynta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce you haue, be euen now as bould with mee, &amp; acquaynt me with the cauſe of your comming.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Idlenes.</head>
                  <p>Syr as you haue ſayd I confeſſe in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery part it is true, I fynd now greate reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doth wiſh me to take in very good part what ſoeuer ye haue alreadye ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, or ſhal hereafter euer ſpeake.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A QVESTION, BY IDLE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes put forth to the Studente.</head>
               <p>SIr, if my vayne and ydle motions, ſhoulde not trouble your graue and well occupyed mynde, I woulde with your patience craue your aduyſe and iudgement in a matter (though verye common and eaſy) wherin at this time my ydle braynes be ſome thing baſyed.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:11754:28"/>
                  <head>Student.</head>
                  <p>My buſines is not ſo greate, but I may very wel afford to graunt you au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyence, and alſo anſweare you if neede ſhal ſo require, &amp; therfore let me heare your mynd, and ſhew mee the trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome and clammye way wherein you, ſticke, and if my ſkill may poſſiblye worke you out a more playne and eaſye paſſage, you ſhall not lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g miſſe of your ſuch earneſt deſire.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Idlenes.</head>
                  <p>Sir, ſince your curteſy is ſo great to bend your ſelf ſo gently, &amp; ſo friendly towards me, I hope I ſhall not neede in haſt to ſcrangle my wittes togeather in vtteryng my mynd at this tyme vnto you, for I haue ſo oftentymes hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, &amp; euen now of late to my coſt, fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> old prouerbe to be true, that haſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth waſt as now wherin I may chuſe I wil rather crepe with the ſnayl, then runne with the Harte: for wee ſee by experience, that the ſloweſt going: Aſſe ys alwayes the ſureſt bearynge beaſt,
<pb facs="tcp:11754:29"/> the ſloweſt winged hauke (if any thing good beſides) doth commonly ſhew the beſt ſport, and kepes her ſelfe longeſt from any miſchaunce: for haſt we ſee y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> many of the femenine ſex, haue ſodayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fallen backwarde to many incurable and great miſhaps, and of men, as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny haue tumbled headlonge forwarde, puttinge themſelues in daunger of as greate perril. do wee not dayly ſe, that many for haſt offer to put meate into their mouthes, gaping full wyde, and yet puts it beſydes? and many w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſpone meates, before their mouthes can be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, chop the ſpone agaynſt their teeth, and all to beſquatter their lippes and beardes if they haue any? do not manye drinke ſo haſtely, as ſometime very ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denlye they almoſt quackle, and choke themſelues, and then (if aſhamed) wil ſay I haue drunke a crum? haue you not knowen diuers men, and ſometyme many women, to fare y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worſe for their ſnatching. Such as can tary tyme and leaſure do co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly fare beſt, &amp; yet I a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tarier thinks always long, vnto
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:11754:29"/> what tyme this tarying muſt haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, I leaue it vnto them of that kind.</p>
                  <p>But to deſcant a litle further vppon this playne and haſty ground: if I ſhal not trouble you to longe: haue you not heard that ſometyme a man hath falue in company by channce with a woman, as it were vppon the frydaye, and hath beddid her vpon ſaterday, wedded her vppon Sunday, and al torepented him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe vppon munday? if repentaunce in ſuch be differd for 2. dayes, it is a mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayle, but if for a weeke, it is a greate wonder: ſuch is the nature of haſt, ſone rype, ſone rotten, ſone hot, ſone colde, ſone done, ſone repented, the wordes of auncient and wyſe men are oftentimes heard among vs, but little regarded of any: they haue ſet downe this for a rule <hi>Quod ſemel faciendum, diu delibera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>du<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:</hi> whatſoeuer is but once to be done, and once done, neuer agayne to bee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done, doth alwayes require greate de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberation, and long to be conſidered of before<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but the Elepha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t being a houge and brutiſh Beaſt without reaſon, doth
<pb facs="tcp:11754:30"/> better obay and follow this rule by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, then we hauing reaſon can by oft and continual perſwaſions: for hee kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing by nature, that if once he chaunce to fall downe he muſt neuer loke to riſe agayne, doth loke ſo narrowlye to his footi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, as he neuer ſetteth ſtep without greate deliberation: when the naturall reſt of ſleepe coms vpon him, he gets him preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly vnto ſome tree, and therto leaning himſelfe ſo taketh his reſt. And is the fall of the Elephant greater to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth, then the fall of a man into a curſt <hi>Xantippa,</hi> or into the handes of an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregious ſhrew? verily I thinke it ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>not poſſibly be, is it not then needful for the man to looke with the Elephant, twiſe aboute him before hee leape: the wyſe man ſayth <hi>inſipientis eſt dicere: &amp;c</hi> it is a greate ſhow and token of an vnwyſe man, when you hear him ſay, if I had knowen this or if I had knowen that, for if raſhiye he bec ſped, it is the beſt wiſedome quietly to whiſt himſelf. I remember a familiar example of a very wyſe and playne man in the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:11754:30"/> who for his patience in bearinge that Kynd of affliction, hath bene kept a long tyme in remembraunce: hee and hys wyfe keeping continuallye ſo cloſe togeather, as ſometyme faſt tyde toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ather by the eares: vnderſtandinge the place and tyme appoynted, where ſuch a famous and learned ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ne ſhoulde preach, they agreed in due time loui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gly to goe togeather arme in arme, and cheeke by checke, preſſing ſo in that lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing maner as nere to the Preacher as poſſibly they coulde. And after a whyle the Preacher entringe into greate diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of many matters, ſeruing fit for his text, among diuers other thinges fell into ſpeach how Chriſt beare hys croſſe, and after many learned and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly exortatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s opened therin, he remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred the ſayinge in the ſcripture: <hi>Who ſoeuer wil bee my ſeruant, muſt take vp his croſſe and follow me:</hi> at which words this honeſt man hauing his wife arme in arme, as though ſharply prickt with a ſodayne motion, ſayd immediat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye vpon a ſodayne vnto the Preacher:
<pb facs="tcp:11754:31"/> Syr, that will I with all my harte, and thervpon preſently hoſting vp his wyfe vppon his ſhoulders as well as he coulde, with al ſpeede began to depart, but the preacher and the reſt of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, blami<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g him as little for that his zealous and godlye mynde, as they greatly maruayled at that his ſtrange &amp; rare example, cauſed him to be ſtaide and eaſed of hys heauy burden, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this the preacher proceeding to hys purpoſe, and finiſhing his Sermon, he cauſed this honeſt man and his wyfe to brought before him in the preſence of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole congregation, and knowing him by report to be a very wyſe ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded openlye of him the cauſe of this ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayne motion: he boldly and openly an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſweared him. Why ſyr was it not your ſaying, that he that wil be the ſeruante of God, muſt do as chriſt did, in takinge vp his croſſe &amp; following him, and that our croſſe that we moſt beare, is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and afflictions of this worlde: the preacher anſweared him it was true, &amp; ſo was the ſaying of the ſcripture, then
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:11754:31"/> ſayd the honeſt man, if this bee true I hope I haue not offended, if I wil be a ſeruant vnto God, I muſt needes cary ſome croſſe, and troubles of this world for I haue hard, that <hi>Nullus ſanctoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> coronatus ſine flagello vel certamine,</hi> and for my part I haue no other croſſe, nor trouble in this world but only this my deare wyfe, who is as diuiliſh a dame, as curſt a ſhrew, as madd a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kin as euer puld man by bearde, and if you haue any other croſſe to tell mee of then her, which I muſt beare, I hope God wil pardon mee, and ſo muſt you, for I know I ſhal not be able to liue to endure y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> burthe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I liue (God knowes) full hardly and wearely with this. The preacher ſayd vnto him: honeſtman I know you are counted wiſe, I find it is for your honeſt and good behauiour y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> you be ſo wel eſtemed of, and not for any gret knowledge or vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding which I thnyke you will clayme vnto your ſelfe: it ſemeth you haue better vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding in your huſbandry, in your oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupation, or in ſome other handcrafte,
<pb facs="tcp:11754:32"/> whatſoeuer it is, then you haue in the knowledge of any Diuine reaſons, but liuing honeſtly and wel (as appears by your good report) and being ſo willing and diligent to geue eare vnto your tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, in that I know euery man cannot be a cunninge clarke (for then manye a theefe ſhould eſcape the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>allous) I do fynde the leſſe cauſe to blame you, but rather I am to inſtruct you according to the truth, which is my office &amp; to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow my tyme in teaching the ignorant people. Therfore you muſt vnderſtand that to beare the croſſe and troubles of this world, it is not to beare them vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your ſhoulders, but you muſt beare the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that is, you muſt indure them, and take them with a quiet and patient mynde, &amp; as a puniſhment ſente from God, for your ſumes. then ſayde the honeſt man vnto him againe. Sir, I confeſſe my ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, and do wiſh that I hadde more knowledge, as for your counſaile I wil willingly fellow as nere I can, my comming was to the ſame purpoſe: but whereas you ſay, I muſt not take nor
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:11754:32"/> beare, the worldlye afflictions vpon my ſhoulders, but indure them w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a patient mynde, I ſay that if you had my wife, or ſuch an other but for one yeare, you ſhould fynd, you muſt not onely indure with a patient mynd, but you ſhould al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo haue ynough to doe, to beare of both with head, ſhoulders, back, &amp; legges, and euery other part of your body: ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, ſir, you ſpeake well, and lyke one of great learning but of litle experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, and God forbid that you ſhould haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> like experience herein as I haue fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, and perhappes many other. The prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher makinge haſt to bee gone, and lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinge anye further at that tyme to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort hym, ſayde, at his departure: ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt man (as it ſeemeth) you are won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully incumbred with a merualous curſt and diuiliſh ſhrewe, farr worſe as appereth moſt true, then the common ſorte of ſhrewes, for they bee all tolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ynough, and by this your report which beareth indeed ſome credit, bei<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ſo honeſt a man, I muſt needs ſay, this
<pb facs="tcp:11754:33"/> wyfe of yours is intollerable, therfore you may do well for your more quiet, &amp; better eaſe, to ſeke ſome lawful ſepeta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion betwixte you, and that is the beſte counſayle that I, or any man els in this caſe canne geue you: for thoughe I haue no experyence, yet by reaſon I fynd there is no ſtryuinge with a diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh dame. I hope there bee not manye ſuch in the worlde, and ſo I leaue you.</p>
                  <p>Then ſayde the other agayne, for all your good counſayie hetherto I harte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thanke you. But now whereas at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wynding vp, you ſeme to geue me cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayle to leaue my deare wyfe. Which is onely the croſſe I haue in this worlde, wherby I muſt goe in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world to come to lyfe euerlaſting. I thinke your doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine therin not to my beſt commodity, and then taking his wyfe by the hande, ſayd vnto her, come wyfe, lette vs goe home togeather agayne, as louingly as wee came forth: and ſince I haue now learned that thou art the only mean to bringe mee to heauen. I will now che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh thee more then euer I did before.
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:11754:33"/> but I hope I ſhall not neede: for if I do by chaunce ſometyme forget you, I hope you wil not forget your ſelfe, and now becauſe you fynd that I haue ſome greater care of you, then heretofore I would be loth you ſhould now ſeeke, by penſiuenes to ſhorten your owne lyfe, for then I may be thought to kill you w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> kyndnes. In this order during his lyfe did this wyſe manne content himſelfe, with hys vnaduiſed and haſty choyſe.</p>
                  <p>More haſt then good ſpeede is neuer to be liked, ſoft fyre maketh ſweete malt, but to take haſt after another ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, they ſay a haſty man maketh a haſty woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, a gentle and ſoft manne doth alwayes make a ſoft and gentle woman: the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty man in rebuking his wyfe openlye. reſembles him that ſpyts into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> winde and receyues it agayne vppon his face: but perhappes you wil ſay that none be of that m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd but women: yes truely it is the mynd of many wyſe men: for exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſake, loke wher you can fynd a wiſe man, that to the ſight of the world, and in very deede will not allowe his wyſe
<pb facs="tcp:11754:34"/> to be mayſter when ſhe liſt, and then on the other ſyde, looke where you can find a foole whoſe wife will not tremble to ſpeake, and be affrayd to loke aſyde of any man in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preſence of him. The wiſe ſcholmayſter ſayth, it is neuer meete to keepe that child in to much awe &amp; feare which by nature is ſo gentle &amp; tractable as the mild<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es of his face, doth alwaies confeſſe his fault, and euen ſo ſayth the wyſe man of the woman, that ſhee yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding alwayes y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> man to be her head, and by nature commonly ſubiecting herſelf willinglye vnto hym, it were a greate fault to keepe her alſo in continual ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection, and therfore amonge wyſe men it is alwayes taken for a rule, the hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble muſt euer be exalted: among the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſort they muſt be contented to bee alwayes oppred, and troden downe, yet ſometyme wee ſee the moſt harebraynd of all is ſurely yokt, and ſtept with the Gooſe from creepinge through euerye hedge, or ſcarce to goe out of anye nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row dore.</p>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:11754:34"/>
                  <p>But looke which way wee will, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther one waye or other, to what ſence ſoeuer this woorde Haſt is beſt &amp; moſt fitteſt to bee wreſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed (vnleſſe that it be a haſty pudding.) I cannot poſſiblye y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magine or thinke whiche waye, or by what meanes it canne well bee allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of.</p>
                  <p>Wee dayly ſee by commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> experince haſty men neuer wante woe, and what thing ſoeuer is done with ouer much haſt, is commonly repented by leaſure.</p>
                  <p>Therefore Syr, I will not at this tyme fall ſodaynlye into the depth of my deſyre here at thys tyme with you, for pleaſures ſake onely: ſince it is the firſt tyme of our meeting togeather, by your patience we wil walke a little to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geather by the waye: and ſith that time doth ſerue vs both ſo well, I would bee gladde to craue your ſhort opinion here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. I haue harde it a queſtion. (beynge dyuers tymes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> my ſelfe in companye) whether it is better to bee ydle, or to be ill occupyed.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:11754:35"/>
                  <head>Student.</head>
                  <p>Friend ydlenes, not vnlyke but you haue bene in companye where this and many other lyke friuolous queſtions haue commonlye bene canuaſed to and froe, and nothing at all vnfit for your e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducation. But if I ſhould take vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me to anſweare this your queſtion, and yeeld a reaſon of ſome betternes in the one of your propoſitions, I hadd neede to pul ſome logition by the ſleeue, as you haue done mee, and craue his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyce, as yon intende to do myne: for as I take it in this your queſtion is inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded an equiuocall and doubtfull ſence, which requireth the artificial tooles of Logicke, to make it ſmooth and playne as wel to the eare as to the eye, and I meane not at this tyme to wade to far, and ſo wantonly with you, I will take your wordes as the lye: and as by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon attendment they are to bee taken, and ſo ſhall you briefly heare myne opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion according to your deſire: you are not to learne, that one queſtion may be anſwered by putti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g forth an other: ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:11754:35"/> my frend, admit a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould bring you two crowes, and demaunde of you whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is the whiter, beyng both (as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly they be) as blacke as a cole: were it poſſible your ſkyll could reach ſo far to yeelde a reaſon the one to bee whiter the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the other? if I knew you were a lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitian, I woulde not doubte but you might do ſom thing w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> your cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ning fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s: but beyng as you are, you muſt be contente to take onely your mother wit, and leaue that ſkilfull art, and by your natural reaſon you ſhall hardlye proue blacke to be whyte, or naught to be good. Therfore your queſtion being this, whether it is better to be ydle, or ill occupyed, I may anſweare you brie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fly, nether barrel better herring: wher you would haue one thinge better then another, you muſt firſt allow the one of them to be good: for better is a degree of compariſon from good, and neither of theſe do good. How then can I iudge which of them is better:</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Idlenes.</head>
                  <p>If I may be bolde to interupt your
<pb facs="tcp:11754:36"/> talke, how would you behaue your ſelf if this queſtion were demaunded, of you in the preſence of ſuch who haue no artificiall ſkyll in reaſoning at all, as if you were amonge a number of women woulde you not ſwarue a whitt from art, and fal to ſome vayne and ydle rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſones you knowe full well that they are neuer brought vp eyther in Logicke or Rethoricke.</p>
                  <p>Therefore amonge them, eyther you muſt talke according to their vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge, or els continuallye bee ſcilente, which would argue much ignoraunce, or rather great dulnes in you.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Student.</head>
                  <p>If I were in companye of neuer ſo many, I confeſſe I could haue very lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle to ſay, I do but I ſhoulde be as the Oule amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g a number of birdes, rather amazed to heare theire continuall chir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, then any waye able to anſweare ſuch kynd of queſtions.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:11754:36"/>
                  <head>Idlenes.</head>
                  <p>Why ſir, and would you alſo lye as the Oule doth, vppon your backe, and crye too witt, too woo? I woulde wiſh you rather to lye grouelyng vpon your belly to hyde yonr baſhful face.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Student</head>
                  <p>Nay frend iniurye, I am no crooked byld byrde, I mynd not ſo to crye, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to fall forward nor backward, the place ſhould be very flippery if I kept not my footing, and beſides, I woulde not grratly ſticke to endeuor my ſelfe to yeeld the beſt reaſons I coulde to feede theire phantaſies, but I am not yet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, we may talke therof at lea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſure: I am now onely in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany of an idle pack, &amp; haue grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted to debate ſom matters w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you, according to our 2 fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſies at this tyme alone. And therfore now to proceede towards the end of my anſwer vnto your headles queſtion, I muſt put you in mynd of a ſentence out of <hi>Tully,</hi> for beyng as I haue ſayd, that your queſtion is of two euils, we muſt proue which is the leaſt, and not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beſt, for ſaith he, <hi>duoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> maloru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> minimu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ma lum eſt elegendum.</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:11754:37"/> of two euilles the leaſt is alwayes to be choſen.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Idlenes</head>
                  <p>Once agayne you muſt pardon me, I muſt be bold to interrupt you. You ſay it is the ſayinge of a wiſe man, that of two or many euils the leaſt is alwayes to be choſen: ſurelye that your ſpeech doth fall out verye well at this tyme to ſerue my turne: for euen now am I to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward a wyfe, and I haue ſtood in great doubt a long tyme with my ſelfe, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther were better to choſe a bigge boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer, or a litle lowbithgrou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d: but by this your ſpeech I fynde now the ende of my doubte. Nowe ſurely I wil ſeeke out the leaſt woman that poſſiblye may bee founde in a cuntrey: and if I may fynde ſuch a one as may ſerue my turne, and yet ſka<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t able to reach vp to my midle, I wil thinke I haue found the moſt preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous iewell in the world: for of two euils you ſay the leaſt is alwayes to bee cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:11754:37"/>
                  <head>Student.</head>
                  <p>Why frend Nimblechaps me thinks you ſeeme rather ready to play with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhadowe of euery thing then wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ling to vnderſtand the ſubſtantiall matter in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing: can you rightly gather vpon my ſpeech that a woman is euill? if you do well vnderſtande mee, you ſhal finde nothing leſſe, but rather that ſhee is for the moſt parte one of the greateſt good thinges in this world, and moſt neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of any thing els beſydes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Idlenes.</head>
                  <p>Syr in what I ſpake of a woman I bilt no part of my ſpeech vpon yours I bilt only vpon my owne ground, your ſpeech was but an introduction vnto me: but if it be as you ſay in your coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey (as for all countryes I am ſure, you haue not trauailed) then do your countrey and myne greatlye differ: for where you ſay, ſhe is one of the greateſt
<pb facs="tcp:11754:38"/> goods in the worlde, there is this olde ſaying with vs. <hi>Femina rara bona, ſed ſi bona digna corona,</hi> a woman is ſoſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and ſo rarely good, that when ſhe is good indeede, ſhe is worthy to wear a crowne of gold: and beſides, wher you ſay, ſhe is moſt neceſſary of any earthly thing<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that ſowndes ſomething like one way to bee true: for wee haue an other old ſaying with vs, that drawes verye neere vnto that purpoſe, which is this that fire, water, and a woman be three of the moſt neceſſary euils in world. with many other lyke olde ſayinges, which were to long to bring in queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Student</head>
                  <p>If al your many, other lyke old, and du<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtical ſayings be like vnto theſe two, none of them all would bee worthye the repeting, for of theſe the one is meerlye falſe, the other not rightly vnderſtoode: for wheras you ſay, that fire, water, &amp; a woman, be three neceſſary euils: that is cleane contrary, for they be three of the neceſſary goods in this world, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preſeruing and keepinge of mans lyfe,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:11754:38"/> and beſides by common reaſon it is a thinge very vnceaſable, that any euill thing can bee neceſſarye, it is rather a thing to be thought neceſſary, that ther were no euill at all: but in way of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning ſome wil ſay, that good beares not his name but in reſpect of euil, and how ſhould good be knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> if euil were not, and that one co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary doth alwayes ſet forth and ſhew an other, &amp; therefore neceſſary with manyother ſtronger re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſons then here can bee made, yet they ſhal be but arguments of deceit, for as black is a colour of it ſelfe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out white &amp; white w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out bearinge ſeueral names for knowledge of the one from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other, euen ſo is good a vertue of it ſelfe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out euil, and euil a vyce of it ſelfe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out good. Therfore I haue ſayd no euil can any way be neceſſary and now ſince a woman by your confeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is neceſſary how wil your ruſty ſentenſes make her to be an euil? my friende, you may ſee howe your olde fayinges (a number of them, by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuance of time be ſo great<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly corrupted, as moſt of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, (bearing a
<pb facs="tcp:11754:39"/> ſhow of truth, in that they be olde) are very falſe. And nowe as to your other ſentence, <hi>Fem. rar. bon. ſed ſi bon. dig. coron.</hi> your interpretation herein is cleane contrary to the true meaninge. For rightly it is thus to be vnderſtood A woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is a rare good (that is to ſay) ſo rare a good thing, as the like is hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or not at al to be found againe in this world, but if good, worthy of a crown of Gold: that is thus to be vnderſtoode on the other ſide, that (ſince in euerye kynd there be alwayes ſome which bee euil) if the woman bee good (ſhee is ſo neceſſary) ſhe is the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> moſt worthy to be had in greate eſtimatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before all other earthly thinges, and therfore it is ſayde ſhee is worthy to be crowned, and now my thinks tyme growes away very faſt I hope we neede not continue any lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger in theſe your ſlippes, and wanton bywayes leading cleane from our pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, you may finde how raſhlye you haue bene ready to conceaue amiſſe: &amp; therfore now once agayne to enter into
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:11754:39"/> your queſtion if you will ſuffer mee to proceed: as I haue ſayd of two euilles the leaſt is to be choſen, and now which is the leaſt euill, to bee ydle or to be yll occupyed, that muſt bee our queſtion: &amp; for this tyme I thynk myne opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wil draw very neere vnto your good liking: For in my conceypt of the twayne, to be ydle is the leaſt euil, and yet I muſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, that ydlenes is the mother of all miſchiefe, the roote of all ſinne the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayd of the deuil, and the deuils ſtael, as the oule is for the byrder vnder his lyme buſh or hydden nett. But to way according vnto common reaſon ſo long as a man is ydle hys mynd is occupyed about nothing of effect, eyther good or bad, and during that tyme in quality he very much reſembleth the Jacke daw, whoſe nature is beyng the moſt vnhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py and ydle headed byrde that flyes, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuallye to plucke ſtrawes from ſome thatcht houſe or other, ſnapping at eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry flie which comes in his way, or ram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of euery litle cranny he fyndes w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſome baggagely ſtuffe. For when ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:11754:40"/> you ſee the ydle man: but eyther he is doyng his neighbour, or next ſtander by ſome petty miſchiefe, catching at flies, playing with ſtrawes vnder his feete, champing them with his teeth, or els buſied about ſome other like ydle occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pations: beyng ydle the mynd alwayes runneth wildly about after euery row<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling glint of the eye, and beinge well markt, it makes the man appeare as if he were mad, and beyng long continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed oft tymes it bringes him to madnes indeede, for then he is a ready hoſt and ſit receptacle to entertayne all wicked imaginations, &amp; hath ſtable romth plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty for the deuil, &amp; as many horſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s as he wil bring, and whether you think y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil daunſing vppon horſbacke within a man wil make him mad or no, I leaue it to your iudgement: we may learne by a familiar example of a ſimile: daylye in experience among vs, that greate inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce doth come by ydlenes For loke vnto thoſe places where greate infecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of plagues and other lyke diſeaſes do raygne: haue you not continuallye there the aduyce of wyſe &amp; learned phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:11754:40"/> in any caſe neuer to goe abroad w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> an empty &amp; ydle ſtomacke (leſt infec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fynding it empty coms in &amp; take his place filling it ful of filthy corruption, &amp; therby bryngeth your body ſoner to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay: they wiſh vnto euery man a thinge moſt eaſy alwayes ready to bee hadd) a cup of ale &amp; a toſt in a morninge, which hath euer bene thought very holeſome, &amp; good to kepe the ſtomacke occupied, though continuall tipling ale knightes in places of miſrule do greatly ſometi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes abuſe it: yet of it ſelf being mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratly take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is neuertheles to be allow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed, &amp; it is worthy of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendation, as ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>peareth by this old verſe following: <hi>ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat, confortat, exhilarat nobilis ala, &amp; dat iucundu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, nappalis ala viruu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> Thus you may ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to kepe your body in perfect health, it is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt neceſſary thinge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> is required at your handes, to kepe it ſtill from emptines: &amp; euen ſo is it w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> your mynd, if you wil kepe it in good order, admit as ſeldom as yon ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany of ydlenes: for beynge ydle you are like a man y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> knoweth a number of mad men
<pb facs="tcp:11754:41"/> to ſtand in a place with naked ſwordes in their handes and yet venters ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>arke naked among them and ſo is killed: and woulde you not iudge this wilfull man guilty of his owne death? ſurely hee is, and although hee cannot liue agayne to this worlde to receaue worldly puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, for that his ſo haynous offence, yet in hell hee is ſure to hange, which is a place of puniſhment euerlaſting for all ſuch like obſtinate, deſperate, and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked offenders and euen ſo is it with you when you are ydle, for then you hazard your ſelfe thus far, you know full well that beyng ydle if the deuil be not with you preſently, he wil not long <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ary fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you: and then if obſtinatly you will ſtill continue in ydlenes, and make him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way to creepe further and further, into your heade, and ſo at length to poſſeſſe your whole bodye, are not you then as guilty of your owne death as he which kylles hymſelfe? if you continue ſo lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g in ydlenes, til the deuil (creping ſo cloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as you can neuer perceaue him) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:11754:41"/> to dip in his foot, then ſurely you are almoſt paſt remedye: but you may ſometyme perchaunce bee ydle, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>et preſently fall to ſome exerciſe agayne, and then it wil be the leſſe hurtful vnto you, ſo long as no vice hath taken poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: and now by this means, ſince ydle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes is but a poſſibility to drawe a man to wicked ſin: and the other, which is to be ill occupyed, is a ſinne in act already committed, thoughe (as I haue ſayd) they be both ſo naught as neuer to be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> allowed: yet of the two in myne opini<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ydlenes is the leſſe euil.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Idlenes</head>
                  <p>Now truly ſyr, my goodwil ſtande<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> vppon thornes, till it hath yeelded d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> thanks according to your deſerued our<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſye, and were it not for the common proue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> be which daily is had in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce, that tomuch of anye thinge is ſtarke naught, I would doubtles ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſome tyme wherein it ſhould app are, I ſhoulde not bee myndful of this your
<pb facs="tcp:11754:42"/> fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſayle: but knowing your haſt vnto other affayres, leaſt I ſhould kepe you to long, I will brieflye proceed ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the firſt cauſe of my commi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g vnto you: and therefore now ſir, this is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other matter, wherin I am to craue your aduiſe.</p>
                  <p>The liuely and cunninge workman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip in the forme and fauoure of a man, ſo far paſſeth, and excelleth all carthlye and artificiall ſkill, as it is not meete to be named in any ſpech of compariſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, with any earthly or worldly thing: and therfore here I dare but faintly ſpeake therof: yet for experience and learning ſake, let me be bould here at this tyme to craue this one thing of you, to ſingle out and choſe ſecretlye vnto your ſelfe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt amiable and well fauoured face that poſſibly may be ſeene, with the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt and moſt cumly parſonage that by any meanes can be found, admitting y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> workemanſhip of nature ſo perfectly ſet forth in hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as not to be reprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dable, ſo much as in one title touchi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge his forme &amp; beautye, and then (committinge your
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:11754:42"/> external ce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſes, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the cumlines &amp; beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of his outward parſonage to ſcile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce) conuay y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſecret inſight of your profou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d iudgement into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> inward partes of the ſaid cumly man, &amp; if there after a while hauing made ſufficient ſerch and view in euery corner, you fynd y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> nature hath not ſo much as vouchſaft one dram of wit in his head, nor ſo much as on good qualitye in his mynd, I praye you then diſſemble not your conceipt in him, but tel me playnly how you woulde eſteme of the man.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Student</head>
                  <p>Your requeſt is verye reaſonable, though ſomthing hard, yet not ſo hard as neceſſary to be vnderſtood: I acompt it hard becauſe (though nature beareth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name) God is the cheefeſt workman, of this moſt cunning and ſkilful peece of worke, which here you haue deſcribed. Therfore if ſodainly I ſhould geue any raſh iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t therin, my ſuch vnaduy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed anſwer would procure y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leſſe credit vnto my ſpeech. But to ſatiſfy your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, my opinion is this: Admittinge
<pb facs="tcp:11754:43"/> him to be according to your deſcription wel fauored and cumly of perſonage, if therwith he hath neyther wit, nor anye one commendable or ſkilful quality be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſydes, yet you ought not any thinge at all to deſpyſe him: for though he differs perhaps greatly from you in beauty &amp; fauour, and ſomethinge in comlines of ſhape (wherin he far excelleth you) and you perhaps differ lykewyſe from him as greatl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in witt with many ſkilful &amp; cunning qualityes of the mynd, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in on the other ſide you do as farre paſſe and goe beyond him. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>et in truth you be both made of one mould, and he that gaue vnto hym that comely parſonage &amp; ſhape of man could as wel haue geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him the vnſeemlieſt ſhape, and forme of the moſt vglieſt beaſt in the worlde, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alſo your great giftes of wiſdome and vnderſtanding, doth likewyſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede, whom as wel he could haue made a very natural foole. and therfore to be ſhort, though ſhauing entred according to your requeſt into the boweiles, and inward partes of this man) I do plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:11754:43"/> ſe that wiſedome &amp; thoſe qualities to be wantige in hym, which do flow in you, and that goodly and cumlye parſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage which is in hym, to be lykewyſe wanting in you: yet I can no way ſee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny great difference of eſtimation which rightly and lawfully ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be had or made betweene you: he is as p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rfite a man in euery part ether outwardly or inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to ſerue that intent and purpoſe, for the which he was made as you, and you as hee.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Idlenes.</head>
                  <p>Sir (not in maner as reprehending you, but with moſt harty thankes) you haue troubled your ſelf further then my intent was in this motion at the firſt to haue troubled you, &amp; done more then I durſt deſire you: my meaning was not to haue craued your iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion in the dutiful &amp; equal eſtimation, which euerye man ought to beare one
<pb facs="tcp:11754:44"/> toward an other, in that wee be al bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and as children of one father: but according to the common courſe of the world (which is, as forreiners &amp; ſtraun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, euerye man to pull out his nexte neighbours throat, for the gayninge to himſelfe a halfepenny) how here would you iudge he ſhould be eſtemed.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Student.</head>
                  <p>As for my trouble it hath not bene greate, for your thankes I do as litle looke, and your mynde I do very well now vnderſtand, and as for myne opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in him accordig to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon courſe of the world, it may ſo fal out, that you &amp; I therin ſhal mecte both in one mind, for the way is ſo playne as a blynd man almoſt may eaſily keepe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> path I think hee ſhall bee taken and reputed in this worlde as a gaye and goodlye paynted ſheath made at the fyrſt for ſome choyſe &amp; ſpecial good mettalled kniues which now (by miſfortune beyng loſt, or raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly caſt awaye) is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>amde full of dyrtye
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:11754:44"/> droſſe, and rotten ſtickes: or otherwyſe as a braue and lofty houſe, erected per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happes at the firſt, and mayntayned longe by ſome famous, wyſe, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Prelates, and now inhabited, by a moſt infamous, ignoraunte, and baſe packe of ſpendalles. Who certainly be perſwaded (bearyng ſo goodly a houſe vppon there heads, thoughe they haue litle witte therin beſydes: and commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as litle money in their purſes) that they bee all in ſuch generall and great eſtimation: as they iudge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> very birds of the ayre, which by chaunce light vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their houſes, comes of purpoſe to yeeld them honor.</p>
                  <p>Wheras of truth, if ſome liberall ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring wyſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were in their roumthes, and by chaunce commttinge ſome ſuch wanton and prodigall ouerſight, they would rather think to themſelues, that thoſe byrdes came for to accuſe them of their vayne and prodigall folly. But contrary to their ſuch moſt ignoraunte and blynde perſwations, the Worlde,
<pb facs="tcp:11754:45"/> doth altogether diſalow and condemne them t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ough perhaps nere vnto theire ſuch ſtatelye and gallante ſeats, many knauiſh diſſembling &amp; ſlattering mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chauntes, wil ſubtelye geue them ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny a cap and legge, more for there meat and drinkes ſake, then eyther for loue or feare, which the prodigall man doth ſy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>dome ſee or vnderſtand, nor yet doth remember the old prouerbe, no craft to the clouted ſhoo, which (but by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> graue wyſe, pollityke, and liberall ſparinge me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) neuer was nor euer ſhal be kept in any good or peaceable order, where one blynde man leadeth an other, they both <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly into ſome dyke, wher two or many fooles be, and one of them appoynted to ouerſee an other. They ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uer ſeaue ſcratching or byting. Wher among many ignorants that haue ſmal vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, as litle wit, &amp; leſſe know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>dge in any thinge at all, one of them notwithſtanding doth alwaies guide, &amp; teach an other, how can they finde, or if as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lynd men by chaunce they ſtumble vppon and finde, how can they keepe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
                     <pb n="33" facs="tcp:11754:45"/> right &amp; playn way, vnto what place ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer they ſeeke: what ioy would therbe (thinke you) among the pore britching boyes, and grammer ſchole children, if it might be lawfull for one of them to gouerne and teach an other, how ioyful would they be if they might haue more mayſters then one or two, or halfe a do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen: for then many a waghalter would be in good hope, that when one of his mayſters for ſome offence ſhould goe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boute to britch him, ſome of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers perhappes for affections ſake wil laboure as faſt to ſaue him, wherof be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge deuided, they may fall into ſome iarre among them ſelues, and thereby the vnhappy wagg may happily eſcape a ſcowring. Truly to be ſhort, I think in euerye thinge, one ignoraunte muſt needes leade an other ignorantlye, one blynd man doth leade an other blyndly, one foole an other fooliſhly: pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ke and put to geather many crafty and ſubtill men, ther ſhall be nothing but deuiſing continually to wrangle, and one to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue an other: knitt likewyſe to toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ather
<pb facs="tcp:11754:46"/> a knotte of knaues, you ſhall ſee nothing but coſenage, quarellig, braw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and fighting. Perhaps you wil ſay to me, then ioyne wyſe men togeather, and they no doubt muſt nedes very wel agree: but the corruption of this world is ſuch, as I fynd by experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce (though it be agaynſt reaſon, in that wiſdome is ſo ſure and perfect a guide vnto them) that they wil oftentymes, and greatly iarre. But where you wil haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and pollecy of man to beare anye ſway, place him not to gouerne and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund his equals, and much leſſe his ſuperiours. But whom is hee to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund and rule? let him bee in place of auctority aboue them, and then eyther for feare or loue they wil obay him.</p>
                  <p>Admit the chiefe captayne in a fielde of equal countenaunce, auctority, and rule with manye of his Souldiers, thinke you that they would le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g agree. I think rather that the whole campe by theire continual diſagrementes, that I am in as greate auctoritye as thou: and I as thou<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> would very eaſily and ſoone be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrowen
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:11754:46"/> and therfore according to wiſedome and pollicy, one cheefe &amp; head ſchole mayſter in euery ſchole, doth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies and only bear the greateſt ſway, though ſomtime he hath diuers vſhers vnder hym: one chief gouerner and ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler in euery field (thoughe with many vnder captaines and petty leaders) and not without great counſayl of wyſe and experte men, doth alwayes beare the ſword of rule, and euen ſo in euery like.</p>
                  <p>But wher you would haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> blinde man wel ledd, let his leader be of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite and ſound ſight, wher you wil haue the crafty diſſemblinge, and ſubtill man the ſimple fooles, the veryeſt knaues, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> common clowted ſhooes, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſortes what ſo euer, kept in their dutyfull due, and cumlye good order, I woulde not haue you couple togea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther like to like, though the olde ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge may bee hadde in remembraunce. <hi>Simile amat ſimile,</hi> for it is moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly proued to be true, that man ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tymes loueth that, which commonly doth him moſt harme.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11754:47"/>
                  <p>But commit them vnder the gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and rod of the moſt graueſt, wyſe, and pollitick vſſhers that poſſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ly may be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ound. Wherby the more likely you ſhall keepe them in awe: and thus my friend to finiſh my anſweare vnto your queſtion, as hear you may perceaue, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great wiſedome and graue gouernme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is not onely needfull and requiſite, but very neceſſary for the mayntenaunce of euery godlye &amp; gorgious houſe, and as well for the gouernment of a common welth, and that no man (haue he neuer ſo gallant or braue a ſeate) is eſteemed in this world and common wealth wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of rule, honor, and dignity, vnleſſe hys wyſedome and pollicy in good go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment be agr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eable therunto, euen ſo is it with your welfauored and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable man, which accordinge to your diſcription wanteth both witte and all good quantyes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Idlenes.</head>
                  <p>Sir you haue not now only reſolued
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:11754:47"/> me of my queſtion but you haue entred (according to your ſaying y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhoulde both meete in a mynde) into the verye ſame path wherein <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> my ſelf had deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined to walke before a turn or two: for though my queſtion was of a moſt wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fauored and ſtrayght <gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>de man, yet y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cauſe therof was this owtward gorgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, &amp; inwarde naked houſe, which you haue here de<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cribed, wherof intending to vſe ſome ſpeach vppon a ſentente of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt famous and learned <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ratour <hi>M. T Cicero</hi> I thought good to be boulde firſt to creepe (by the ſayd ſimile of the man) into ſome part of your iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t therin: wherin now with moſte hartye thankes you haue verye wel ſerued my turne</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Student.</head>
                  <p>If I haue any way pleaſured you, I am very glad but whereas it ſeemeth by your wordes, your intent was to vſe ſome ſpeach, let not anye thinge that I haue ſayde, hinder or ſtay your procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb facs="tcp:11754:48"/> for if it be well or any thinge tollerable I wil allow therof: if otherwyſe I wil wiſh it amended.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Idlenes,</head>
                  <p>Sir nothing doubting of your friendly acceptau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and good counſayle: this is the ſentence whereupon I firſt groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded my purpoſe and intente.</p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>M. T. Cicero.</bibl>
                     <p>Non domo dominus, ſed domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no domus honoranda est.</p>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>Idlenes</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>VVho liſt to build a lofty houſe,</l>
                     <l>intending there a portly ſtate</l>
                     <l>Had neede lay vvel his vvits in ſouſe,</l>
                     <l>to keepe them freſh vvithin his pate.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>A pouldring tub if rightly vſd,</l>
                     <l>and ſeaſond duely to his kinde:</l>
                     <pb n="36" facs="tcp:11754:48"/>
                     <l>VVhich alvvayes yeeldes his liquor ſvveete:</l>
                     <l>and pleaſde the taſt of euery mynd.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>For buildinges braue be eaſ'ly made</l>
                     <l>but hardly then they be mayntaind,</l>
                     <l>If not by trickes of vviſedoms trade,</l>
                     <l>vvhich teach vayne toyes to be refrainde,</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But he that ſhould ſuch toyes ſet dovvne</l>
                     <l>as vviſedome vviſh vve ſhould not vſe,</l>
                     <l>Might ſee him ſelfe in folly drovvne</l>
                     <l>in that moſt men vvould him refuſe</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>For vvho ſees not the vvorld is bent</l>
                     <l>to pompe and prayſe in euery thing,</l>
                     <l>And nothing vvell if vviſely ſyent</l>
                     <l>hath eyes, but they be flattering.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Conceipts of coſt, vvithout meaſure,</l>
                     <l>are novv ſo grovven into delyte.</l>
                     <l>As vvhere no toy there no pleaſure,</l>
                     <l>vvhich pleaſeth not the vvanton ſight.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Therefore ſynce vve haue vvealth at vvill</l>
                     <l>and tyme in pleaſure minde to ſpende,</l>
                     <l>To haue of our delites our fill,</l>
                     <l>let vs our ſelfe ro feaſting bend.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:11754:49"/>
                     <l>And novv hovv ſhall th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s pleaſant day</l>
                     <l>or drouſey if it ſo befall,</l>
                     <l>Be brought to end and paſt avvay?</l>
                     <l>Good cheere ſayth ſome is beſt of all,</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>And then novv vvhether ſhall vve ſayle,</l>
                     <l>to him ſayth one, vvhere daynty fare</l>
                     <l>And delicates do neuer fayle.</l>
                     <l>nor yet of coſt is any ſpare.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>For there a vvorld of vvanton vvightes</l>
                     <l>vveſhall not miſſe, but fynde moſt braue</l>
                     <l>VVe can not vviſh for more delightes</l>
                     <l>then there at all tymes, vve may haue.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>VVe ſhall not there be bid vvelcome</l>
                     <l>to ſuch poore fare as vve ſhall fynde,</l>
                     <l>Nor yet ſee thinges onely handſome,</l>
                     <l>but paſſing fyne of euery kynd.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>For biefe, veale mutton, pork or ſouſe,</l>
                     <l>geeſe capons<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> hens vvith all ſuch like<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>They feede the ſerua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ntes in the houſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>and all of Dayntyes v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e muſt picke,</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>VVith <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>auſy ſallets of al ſorte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="37" facs="tcp:11754:49"/>
                     <l>of taſt pleaſaunt, vvith coſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> plenty<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>VVherof an hundred by reportes,</l>
                     <l>vvill hardly one mau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>atiſfy.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>No common bread vve ſhall neede eate</l>
                     <l>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> caſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>, tovvers, and tovvnes of golde</l>
                     <l>In ſuget paſte, vvith coſt ſo great</l>
                     <l>as ſildome hath the like bene could</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Nor yet neede vve drinke ale or beare,</l>
                     <l>choyſe of VVines be there ſo plenty,</l>
                     <l>And dainty lippes fit for ſuch cheare</l>
                     <l>that houſe is neuer longe empty.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Therfore novv let vs (as I ſay)</l>
                     <l>ſince tyme of pleaſure ſerues ſo vvel</l>
                     <l>Goe paſſe avvay this pleaſant day</l>
                     <l>vvith him that beares avvay the bell.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>Student.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Oh friend I ſigh to heare your vayne,</l>
                     <l>and hovv this vvanton vvorld is bent</l>
                     <l>To bring a virtue in diſdayne,</l>
                     <l>vvhich is vvhen vvealth is vviſely ſpent.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>For then it ought to be of right,</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:11754:50"/>
                     <l>accompted liberality</l>
                     <l>VVhen othervviſe in vviſedomes ſigh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>it is but prodigality,</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>If this vvhich you haue ſayd be true</l>
                     <l>as ſeemes experience hath you taught</l>
                     <l>VViſdome might make your hart to ru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>that you ſo oft ſuch vice haue ſought.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>Idlenes,</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>VVhy ſyr, ſay you thus of to this,</l>
                     <l>as though it vvere a payne to heare</l>
                     <l>Young men delight in fantaſies</l>
                     <l>vvith honeſt mirth and daynty cheare.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>Student.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I truely it is thought a payne</l>
                     <l>to all vvile <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>en that euer vvrote</l>
                     <l>That heads ſo young ſhould beat their brain</l>
                     <l>to ſtroy ſuch as they ſpye to do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e:</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>For vviſdome vvarneth vs to reach</l>
                     <l>the ignorantes hovv to auoyde</l>
                     <l>Deſtruction, yea vvracke, or breach</l>
                     <l>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>pying them thervvith annoyde</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>And not to trippe the blynd man dovvne,</l>
                     <pb n="38" facs="tcp:11754:50"/>
                     <l>vvith ioy to ſee him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>umbling there</l>
                     <l>For ſo you may deſerue the crovvne</l>
                     <l>of knauery vvhich many vveare,</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The vvhich I vvould be loth to ſee</l>
                     <l>my frend ſhould vveare a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>token playne</l>
                     <l>Of fol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>y fyxt in him to bee.</l>
                     <l>vvhich vvith the vviſe bread great diſdayne</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But ſince vve be all vvell agreed</l>
                     <l>to paſſe ſometime in pleaſant cheare</l>
                     <l>VVe vvil not ſeeme to hunt for neede</l>
                     <l>nor yet to buy our ſport ſo deare</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>That vvith returne our friendes ſhall ſee</l>
                     <l>our credits are ſo crackt vvith ſhame</l>
                     <l>As ſome ſvveete ſyrupe ſuckers be.</l>
                     <l>for then of right deſerue vve blame.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Such vvanton ſteppes vvevvil not tread<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>as to allure our friendes to charge.</l>
                     <l>Since captayne Vanity ſuch doth leade,</l>
                     <l>as loue to cloy their friends at large</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>For by ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>oyes as you haue namd,</l>
                     <l>it is vvell knovvne that many men</l>
                     <l>Of much greate vvealth haue bene ſo lamde,</l>
                     <l>as novv to begging they muſt leane.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:11754:51"/>
                     <l>VVho therfore vvill be partener.</l>
                     <l>vvith ſuch vayne vvanoring heads at all,</l>
                     <l>Muſt thinke himſelfe the vvoithier</l>
                     <l>to beare ſuch blame as doth befall.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But if you vvill take my aduyſe,</l>
                     <l>vvith ſuch delightes as I thinke good</l>
                     <l>VVe vvill not chuſe our fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e ſo niſe,</l>
                     <l>nor yet ſuch Oſte of vvanton mood.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The auntie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t houſe vve all knovv vvel,</l>
                     <l>vvhich ſhoring ſtandes vppon the hill,</l>
                     <l>VVhere ſuch vvere euer vvont to dvvel,</l>
                     <l>as alvvayes had their vvit at vvill:</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>They euer tooke delite to leane</l>
                     <l>vnto the ſaying of the vviſe,</l>
                     <l>That meaſure is a meary meane</l>
                     <l>and pleaſe al men of honeſt guiſe,</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>VVhich hath them taught to guide ſo right,</l>
                     <l>that houſe in hoſpitality,</l>
                     <l>As come or goe by day or night.</l>
                     <l>they vvil not feed your iolity</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But for all plenty of good fare,</l>
                     <l>no place to bountye more is bent,</l>
                     <l>You ſhall not there fynd diſhes bare</l>
                     <pb n="39" facs="tcp:11754:51"/>
                     <l>nor yet ſee vvant of vvhat is ſpent</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>As for paſtimes, vvith plaſures fit,</l>
                     <l>for gentlemen both young and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ld,</l>
                     <l>You can nor vviſh by any vvit,</l>
                     <l>more meate, if you be vviſely bould.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>And can your vvh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>es ſo vvind at vvill,</l>
                     <l>as to be fitt at each rebound.</l>
                     <l>To mayne vvith ſome prety ſkill</l>
                     <l>the balle of vvit vvhich toſt is round.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>For there you ſhal not only haue</l>
                     <l>your hunger fed vvith holeſome cheare<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>But you ſhal fynd delight to craue</l>
                     <l>ſuch pleaſures oft to ſee and heare.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>It is not like your gluttons fare</l>
                     <l>vvhich happily laſteth for a yeare</l>
                     <l>For here a vviſe man rules vvith care,</l>
                     <l>and ſcrapes avvay all folly cleare.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Therfore ſince novv vve be ſo light</l>
                     <l>as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>apors, vvhich the ſunne dravves vp</l>
                     <l>To be alluerd by vveather bright,</l>
                     <l>let vs firſt drinke of follyes cup.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:11754:52"/>
                     <l>And then if all agree thereto</l>
                     <l>this ydle tyme to paſſe avvay,</l>
                     <l>As marchpaind mouthed vvantons do</l>
                     <l>vve vvil ſoone ſpend this pleaſaunt day</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>And thus vvee ſee in euery place</l>
                     <l>moſt men to this haue greate deſire.</l>
                     <l>VVith vvho ſhall ſhovv the luſtieſt face</l>
                     <l>in coſtly, fyne, and braue attire,</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>VVhich yeeldes them honor as they thinke,</l>
                     <l>in places vvhere they be not knovvne<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>And ſo from place to place they ſlinke.</l>
                     <l>and vveares perhaps more then their ovvne</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>VVherby ſuch thankles gluttons feede</l>
                     <l>themſelues ful oft in many a place</l>
                     <l>VVhere many ſuch as haue more neede</l>
                     <l>dare not for ſhame once ſhevv their face.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>For he that vveares not cloth of gould</l>
                     <l>vvith <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>atten, veluet, or ſuch like</l>
                     <l>Muſt not among ſuch gay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> be bould,</l>
                     <l>as though he ſhould his mates there ſeeke</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>VVhen he perhaps that vveares his cote</l>
                     <l>moſt playne i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> oft the better man,</l>
                     <l>VVhich vviſe men alvvayes vvel do note:</l>
                     <l>and yet mend none do vvhat they can.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb n="40" facs="tcp:11754:52"/>
                     <l>But ſuch as pedlers packes do bear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>if they by vvealth aduaunced be</l>
                     <l>He that ſhould ſpy them fitting there,</l>
                     <l>and tell them of this fond decree.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Might luckely leape to ſaue his head</l>
                     <l>from knockes, if they might him vvel rea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>For that in ſteed of ſuger breade.</l>
                     <l>he ſliceth them ſuch ſovver leach.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>And yet to end I do admit</l>
                     <l>the meaneſt man deſerue may vvell</l>
                     <l>Among the beſt ſometyme to ſit</l>
                     <l>if vvealth be vvonne by great trauell.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Or els by virtue of learning</l>
                     <l>vvhich doth the meaneſt man of all</l>
                     <l>(As our experience dayly bring)</l>
                     <l>to honor high moſt eaſely call.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>VVherto vvhen they aduaunced be,</l>
                     <l>by force of virtues paynful trade.</l>
                     <l>They vvel deſerue in their degree</l>
                     <l>ſuch honor as by lavves are made</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>And yet from vvhence the vines do ſpring</l>
                     <l>of all virtues that euer vvere,</l>
                     <l>As in the ſcholes of deepe learning,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſvvarme, vvho beſt ſhould bea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:11754:53"/>
                     <l>But there they reſt and all agree,</l>
                     <l>as bees vvhich buze abroad avvhile,</l>
                     <l>That learning vvel deſerues the fee</l>
                     <l>of honor great, vvith noble ſtyle.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>And he vvhoſe vvits moſt vviſely vvreſt</l>
                     <l>nobility longeſt to preſerue,</l>
                     <l>Muſt beſt be thought among the reſt</l>
                     <l>of right his honor to deſerue.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Idlenes</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ir, you haue nowe bound me by dutye to gieue you moſt hartye thankes that thus frie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly you haue bene contente (for this ſhort time) to baniſh your ſelfe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your ſo earneſt, graue, and profound ſtudye, to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany me with your friendly conceipt in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſe my dayne and ydle inuentions. And therfore now leſt I ſhould ſo long here at this tyme keepe you walkinge
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:11754:53"/> with mee in this my path of vanity, as hereafter when wee ſhall haue like oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation to trouble you in crauinge your co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany agayne, you ſhall be vnwilling to graunte the ſpendinge of any time (which is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt precious <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ewell in the whole world) with ſuch an endles bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſye, and ydle runninge brayne: I leaue heare at this tyme to trouble you any further, commending you vnto God, &amp; to your ſeate and chayre of ſtudye from whence you came.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Student</head>
                  <p>Friend Idlenes, though perhaps I am not ſo curious or coy in ſpending of my tyme for good felowſhip and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany ſake, as you ſuppoſe and think me to be: yet I may not any waye blame you, but rather do very well allow of this your ſuch ready conceipte, &amp; reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable ſpeech, wherin you ſeeme not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vnwilling greatly to aſſure or intiſe me vnto any folly: But alſo as loth, long to hould or kepe mee in anye path
<pb facs="tcp:11754:54"/> of ydlenes or vanity. For true it is, that notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding moſt willingly hether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, I haue concented to beſtowe both tyme and ſpeech accordinge to your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt: yet as true it is, I would be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry loth to conſume or ſpende any longe tyme in ſuch friuolous and vayne deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. Thoughe for the companye of my frend I can ſomtyme be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent to wade w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> him in ſome ſmoth, cleare &amp; ſhallow flaſh of folly: yet I confeſſe I would be very loth to aduenture ſo far with him as to ſwim in any rongh, darke, or bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomles pit or puddle of wicked &amp; fylthe vice. I would bee loth with a kinge to drowne in follye, though with my me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aneſt frend (as I haue ſayd) I can bee content to wade therein: willinglye I would not (if I could otherwyſe chuſe) goe to farre in any thing. But bearing alwayes in mynde the warninge of a wyſe manne to leaue the Racke, and Maunger, and to take a ſnatch and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye, with ſmall hyndraunce vnto any of my wayghty affayres. I can at anye
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:11754:54"/> tyme in anye honeſt and cumlye toye of delighte or pleaſure, recreate my ſelfe and accompany my frend.</p>
                  <p>But now as ſeemes vnto mee, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happes you haue an ydle and wanton turne or two ſecretly to walke by your ſelfe, wherein you would not haue mee willingly behold your geſture: &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore cunningly crauinge the riddaunce of my companye (as though for feare of offence) you comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d me to my chayre, whereunto beyng verye well content to graunt you your ſuch ſecrete, and cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning requeſt, I am as willing to goe, and in likemanner as you commended me vnto God, I alſo in the ſame friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly manner, commend you not vnto him but to your owne inuention. Wiſhinge you to remember your owne coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayle now in your ſelfe, &amp; not to walke to long in any your pathes of vanity. Yet I doubte verye much (friende I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dlenes) to diſſwade you fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vanity, for it wil moſt certaynly perſwade a great number to accuſe mee of vayne follye,
<pb facs="tcp:11754:55"/> and perhaps I may ſo deeply incurre <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> diſpleaſure of ſo many as durynge lyfe euer after, (turne which way I will) the blame of my ſuch folly<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſhall ſtil con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually be blowen in my face: for ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting curioſity aſyde, to be playne, when your thicke, and buſhye bee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> heade (in ſhape much like to a hedge hogge halfe vncloſing himſelfe, and ſhewinge his bare and naked face) lieth rowled vnder an aperne, and tumbling in your ſweete harts and wanto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, buſying the wabling belclarppe of your ſo vayn and ydle body, ſo greatlye to her good lyking and pleaſure euery wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, as ſhee ſeemeth not onely loth to leaue your company, but rather longing ſtil to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue her ſuch paſtyme, in playing with the ſoft and gentle prickes of that your rowlinge and ydle pate, and ſometyme perhaps at your oft requeſt and flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring intiſement: yeelding w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> her ſmoth and tender lips to honor your hard and bruſelled mouth. If then (this merry gale of wynde, this ſturring betwixte you, cuppling your ſhips to gether, and
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:11754:55"/> ſayling outward in your voiage of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighte) you bluntly by chaunce ſhoulde boulte cute this my friendly perſwaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (though ſecretely vouchſafed vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you) moning my ſpeach the cauſe of your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture, vnto that your louing &amp; wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton mouſe, and in the middeſt of al your pleaſure offer ſo to departe, then ſhall my ſecret, (though vndeſerued) &amp; pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching paynes begin, then ſhall I be ſo toſte from tounge to tounge, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mouth to mouth, from place to place, and ſo ſharply and ſhrewiſhly ſhake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vp amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ſo many, as doubtles it were a thouſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d tymes better for any man, in the like pitiful caſe a mong them (though not as a dogge) to be toſt in a blanket: they will ſay, let olde grayberde keepe his counſayle to himſelfe. We will craue at his hands, his graue aduiſe, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we thinke good: becauſe now by continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of tyme, he is become fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a clarke to a parriſh prieſt, could he now be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to haue no clarkes at all? could hee now fynd in his hart to be reader, ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and belringer, and al in his pariſh
<pb facs="tcp:11754:56"/> alone, ſurelye it were not amiſſe if hee were wel applyed, and kept to his tac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kle but one moneth, and then no doubt wee ſhall ſee him come creeping laſiſy home with weary limnies: and then yf any man wil offer to take a rope out of his hand, you ſhal ſee hee will be as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ady &amp; as willing to let it goe as euer he was in his life to take it vp: then ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after, you ſhall heare he wil as open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly publiſh it, to be a deede of charitye to helpe the weake and ſurcharged ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as he hath alreadye ſecretly whiſpered in diſalowing the wanton ſeruice of the ſtronge and youthful bodyes, and then will confeſſe that a helping hand is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to be blamed, &amp; eſpetially in thoſe thinges which muſt needes be done.</p>
                  <p>Therfore waying wel the vanity of his ſpeech, let vs not ſo eaſilye parte, as to breake of all good company for a white hayre. Frend Idlenes I know this wil be their ſaying: &amp; beſydes this, I know you haue many ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers on, very dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; daily ſtudients, deſirous to immitate you in this your ydle art, and to learne
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:11754:56"/> your cunning ſlayghtes in rockinge in Venus lappe, prickinge in, and pick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng out ſometymes pinhes out of her pi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>caſe, thrumming of apern ſtrings &amp; with many other ydle deuiſes: and ther fore friend iniury, ſince in diſſwadinge you accordinge to my former ſpeech, I ſhal ſeeme toper ſwade many a thouſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d from that which they wil be verye loth to leaue, and in ſo vaynly waſtinge my wynde ſhall appeare as much an ydle packe as the beſt, I recante my former perſwaſion, and thus do commend you only heare vnto your naturall, vayne, &amp; ydle inuentions.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Idlenes.</head>
                  <p>Sir you ſeeme ſo gameſome &amp; plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaunt in this your reply vppon my late and friendly farewell, as I thinke you could be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent to remaineſtil w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> me, ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing your ſelfe in this my laſye tub (as you terme it) and veſſel of ydle vanity: therfore know this I am not ſo inclind vnto y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vice of ingratitude, I haue bene ſo
<pb facs="tcp:11754:57"/> vnciuiſly or ſo vnmannerly brought vp<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that when any man friendly vpon good wil, as though deſyrous of my compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, ſhal come vnto me, that then after <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> whyle eyther by ſecret ſpeeches or cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning geſtures, I wil ſeeme ſo weary of him, as rather deſyrous of his rou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>th then of himſelfe, for truly it is nothing agreable eyther vnto my nature or to my bringing vp and much leſſe, when I my ſelfe ſhall be firſt deſirous of his company. But I muſt confeſſe you are blameles, though you did miſtake me, for you cannot be ſo well acquaynted w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> my nature and meani<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g in any thing: as I am with the naturall diſpoſition of you, and of all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world beſides. I agree well with you, if I were according to the common nature and diſpoſition of men, beyng in company w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> my friendes and familiars, I woulde ſometymes wiſh, and perhappes willinglye c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aue rather their roumth then their compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny. For admitting I weee as other me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bee, and as you your ſelf in your youth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full dayes heretofore haue bene: then
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:11754:57"/> perhaps and not vnlike but it might be with me as it hath bene with you &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others, that ſome famous learned, &amp; ſkilfull Aſtronomer, hath latelye bene with me, and by his or her miſticall and wonderfull ſtraunge knowledge, hath geuen me certaynly to vnderſtand, that ſuch a tyme, day and hower, and in ſuch a place there ſhal without fayle appear vnto me very ſecretly a glorious, braue and goodly blaſing ſtarre: and that the place where it ſhal appeare, muſt needs be free, and cleere of al company, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe it will ſhew it ſelfe but as a playne and common ſtar, without any blaſing or ſtemming at all. Perhappes I haue appoynted ſecretlye to ſee ſome tum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling caſt, with ſome pleaſant and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſlayghtes of iugling trickes, and to draw more nerer vnto natural &amp; playne vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, not vnlike but I haue ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted to kis ſome pretye wench in a corner: and now admittyng al this to be true (as in many men it is daily ſeene, would any of my friendes, or acquayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance blame me, to ſhew the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cunningly
<pb facs="tcp:11754:58"/> ſome colour of deſire to craue for a time rather their roumth then their compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, I thinke none. There is alſo an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther kynd of people, which do likewiſe and very often cunningly craue the rid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunce of company, which be in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh fraſe, the cormugions and coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous carles of this worlde, their natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral diſpoſition is, fyrſt to ſcramble and ſcratch togeather if he ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a liuing equal with the beſt yeman, gentleman, or ſquyre in his countrey, then ſtryuing to ſhroude himſelfe vnder ſome ragged &amp; little cottage, to ſerue no further then onely for neceſſity, or if a large or fayre houſe, then keeping his dores continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſhut as though neuer at home, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenting hymſelſe willinglye, and all his houſhold perforce with a ſparinge and pinching dyet, doth chiefly feede and al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>togeather delight himſelfe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the oft tel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ling and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinual ſight of his money, as young men commonly do themſelues, in the ſight of their louers. And now ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mit ſome young heads and merye com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions knowing his abilitye &amp; vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:11754:58"/> his miſerable &amp; beggerly mind huſying their brayns cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ningly to work him ſom ſlayghty, prety, &amp; ſlipry trick, doe agree among the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues vpon ſome high &amp; feſtiual day, knowing y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps he hath a peece of biefe, a calues <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ad or an oxe foote in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pot, &amp; do apoint <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> meeting of many neighbours y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> verye ſame tyme to dyne with him, bidden by a meſſenger in very good &amp; due order, as though very ſollomly bidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by him: then dinner time drawing nere, ſeruice beyng done, &amp; euery man departinge to his houſe, this pore, miſerable &amp; wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched miſer doth ſit ſtil in his ſeate fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring greatly that if ſodaynly he ſhould thronge or preſſe out among the thick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, ſome or other would ſo cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ingly mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter ſuch occation of talke with him, as eyther to ſhame him or els to inforce him home to dinner, but after a whyle looking oftentymes backward ouer his ſhoulder, and ſpying ſome ſtil remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nig behynd, not muſing a litle at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nig therof, at le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth riſe th vp, &amp; pulling his cap in his eyes, paſſeth away by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <pb facs="tcp:11754:59"/> ſneaking, as though he had nothinge to ſay or meddle with any of them all: but then euerye man ryſinge vp<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> with him, greatly to his admiratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and honoring him with cap and legge, accepting that hys geſture as a ſtately and graue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauiour in him. Some of them acco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany him check by cheek with friend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y commendation, and great thankes for his vnwonted and friendly curteſy: and the reſt following after hard vppon his heeles, playnly to his ſight intendinge to accompany him home to dynner, as they thinke like bidden and welcome gueſtes, but as he thinkes like malla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t impudent, and ſauſy marchaunts: if now it were poſſible to beholde euen at this inſtant, with our outward eyes, the ſtrange thoughts and ymaginatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of this pore, diſtreſſed, and miſerable miſer. I think the merieſt company of ſtage players, that might be founde in a cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey, would hardly make more ſport then he him ſelfe would do alone: for to ſee how glummiſhly hee glyeth aſide, like a bere at a ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ake, and how manye
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:11754:59"/> ſtoppes and turnes he makes before he comes home, and how priuily he ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>neth them, wiſhing the Deuill and his dam to choke them all, the ſight thereof no doubt, if it were poſſible one horſe face might laugh at an other, woulde make any horſe in the world to break his hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, I can but wiſh that I hadde eyther <hi>Apelles</hi> or <hi>Zeuxes</hi> ſkil, in the ſcience of paynting and that I could as perfectly paynt him, with his countenaunce ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to my imagination, as <hi>Zeuxes</hi> paynted his grapes, or as <hi>Apelles</hi> his ſheete, which were ſo cunninglye done on both partes, as euer ſince to bee had in great eſtimation, but neuer to bee paternd: the one of them <hi>Zeuxes,</hi> (as our bookes do report) amonge many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of his notable workes, paynted (as before named) a naked boy with a bu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch of grapes as though growing vpon his ſhoulders, which were ſo perfite to the outward ſight, as the very byrdes of the ayre, came and lited vppon the boyes ſhoulder &amp; continually picked vpon the grapes, and though they found no ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>:
<pb facs="tcp:11754:60"/> yet as appeared by their oft reſort, they could not be perſwaded, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grapes they muſt needes bee, and in that they could neuer pick out any iuice, they ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med rather to impute it to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bluntnes of the bylles, then to the dryneſſe of the grapes: for they went continually to a ſtone which was faſt by, and alwayes whet their bylles and ſo ſtill continued their reſort vntil it was taken awaye. The other paynter <hi>Apelles</hi> hearing of this excellent peece of worke, deſtred <hi>Zeuxes</hi> that a day might be appoynted of meetinge betwixte them two before ſome gentlemen of their friendes &amp; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, and to paſſe away ſomtyme, and to delight the ſight of their friends deſyred him to bringe of his workes, what he thought good, &amp; that he would do the like, wherunto <hi>Zeuxes</hi> agreyng at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> day appoynted among many other wonderful, ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge, and notable works he brought this naked boy w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grapes vppon his ſhoulders, <hi>Apelles</hi> amonge diuers other lyke wyſe very cuning and ſkilful works, brought a table couered
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:11754:60"/> with a white ſheete, &amp; then in viewing euery man the others workes, <hi>Apelle</hi> greatly commended y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> perfit colour and forme of the grapes, &amp; nothing diſalow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of al the reſt: &amp; then <hi>Zeuxes</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge likewiſe (no otherwyſe then iuſt cauſe doth require) the per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>it workma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip in each point of <hi>Apelles,</hi> deſired af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter all y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he would take away the white ſheete which couered his table, for hee would be glad if he might to ſee all, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <hi>Apelles</hi> ſmiling to hymſelf ſayd, friend <hi>Zeuxes,</hi> ſince you are ſo deſirous, I wil not be ſo ingrateful as to deny you: yet my meani<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g was whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I firſt brought it not euer to vncouer it, becauſe I founde ſome fault with my ſelfe therin, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore was the more loth to ſhow my fault vnto ſtraungers: but ſince you haue don all this at my requeſt, I wil not herein denye you yours: therfore euen at your pleaſure goe and take it of your ſelf, for I will bee loth to condempne my ſelfe, I hadd rather an other manne ſhoulde condempne me. Then ſaide <hi>Zeuxes,</hi> na friende <hi>Apelles,</hi> if ſo bee y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you doubte
<pb facs="tcp:11754:61"/> any diſcredite therby. I will not deſire it for any money. But <hi>Apelles</hi> anſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringe: I force not for the diſcredite a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong my frendes: take it of and ſpare not. Then <hi>Zeuxes</hi> drawing nere vnto it as one with chyld, til he had ſeene what was vnder, layd both his handes vppon it at both ſides, catchinge to take holde of the ſheete, and ſuddaynly finding it to be but a paynted colour and no ſheete in truth turnde him aboute agayne, with great admiration, &amp; ſayd among the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al, that wheras <hi>Zeuxes</hi> had cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ningly (as the world thought) deceiued the birds. <hi>Apelles</hi> hath here more cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ningly decei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued <hi>Zeuxes,</hi> for where as in truth I thought to haue take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of a ſhete, I haue but ſcratchte at a paynted coloure of white: &amp; thus with many other pleaſant and prety conceiptes <hi>Apelles</hi> at y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> time bare away the bell. And now if I had lyke ſkil vnto eyther of theſe, whether thinke you that my t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>me ſpent in payn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of this man would be loſt or no. But it is wel knowen (the more is the pitye for this man) I am neither <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelles</hi>
                     <pb n="49" facs="tcp:11754:61"/> nor <hi>Zeuxes,</hi> but playne ydlenes. And therfore nothinge meete to paynte him out ſo orderly as the natural ſhape and countenaunce of the manne doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire.</p>
                  <p>But leauing the pleaſant ſhow vnto the cunning paynter, &amp; admitting this to be true (as I thinke it hath bene put in vſe) could you or any man els blame this ſylly miſerable, &amp; wretched mucke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munger or the world to be rather deſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous of the roumth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the company of theſe ſecret inuited &amp; bidden gueſtes: ſurely for my part I thinke you cannot but rather you muſt holde him excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</p>
                  <p>Therfore ſyr, to conclude this my lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g and tedious ſpeech perhaps vnto you. If I were (as I haue ſayde before) a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable with the common courſe and nature of men, you might wel haue ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered by my ſpeech, that I was deſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous of your roumth and cleanlye ryd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunce. But myne eſtate &amp; callinge is ſuch, as no company, be it euer ſo great can impoueriſh me, or diminiſh or take
<pb facs="tcp:11754:62"/> away any delite from me at all. For the more co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panye, the greater is my riches and delite if they wil conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t themſelues with mee and any dyet: I am none of Shamfaſtes children, I bluſh not who<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſoeuer lookes vppon mee. And therfore thinke not that I did commend you vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your ſtudy, becauſe I was deſirous (as you tooke it) to daunce a turne or two priuily or wantonly alone.</p>
                  <p>For ſince you ſeeme ſo willinge and contente with my company, with al my harte, I will make you partaker in all the reſte of my cauſes, which at this tyme I intende to bringe in queſtion, &amp; beſydes, rather then you ſhal thinke me (as you haue thought) weary of your company. If you wil accept of this my arte and ſymple ſkyll. I came and will afford you, for euery hower in the day, for euery day in the yere, and for euery yeare durynge your lyfe, ſeueral que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, with many pretye conceiptes at all tymes to buſy and occupye your ſelfe withall: as preſentlye ſhall appeare, yf you will vouchſafe vnto mee your
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:11754:62"/> friendly audience.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Student</head>
                  <p>Friend Idlenes, you ſay, and true it is, that you are acquaynted with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and diſpoſition of all eſtates, far better then I am, or euer ſhal be able to conceiue, and that by reaſon of your lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g experience and continual company with all men: then muſt I needes now think and certaynly perſwade my ſelfe, that you are not now vnacquaynted, nor to learne the qualityes of a knaue. There is an old ſaying and oftentymes founde to be true. <hi>ni, fa, pa, con:</hi> admitte you were a teacher of the common people, or a ſcholemayſter ouer manye children as no doubt ſomtime you are, beyng a great medler, and buſye bodye in any thing, &amp; dayly intruding your ſelfe into euery vocation, &amp; calling from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt to the loweſt whatſoeuer, as a moſt ydle &amp; mery co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panion: ſtaring as bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye vppon a Kinge as you doe vppon the meaneſt &amp; playneſt begger: if a man
<pb facs="tcp:11754:63"/> may aſke you a queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: how would you open vnto the common people, or howe would you teach your younge ſchollers to vnderſtand the meaninge of theſe 4. wordes, <hi>ni, fa, pa, con.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Idlenes</head>
                  <p>Sir I am no more nice in aunſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring then I am in putting forth. But to tell you the truth (which I thinke you do already know) it pertaynes nothing at all vnto mee to be a teacher, though ſometymes I confeſſe I am in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny with manye wyſe and learned men. for where I acompany moſt, there they learne and teach leaſt: &amp; litle or nothing tendinge to goodnes, is euerbrought in queſtion, vnleſſe it be at a verye greate chaunce: and then alſo am I fayne to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part as one whoſe companye is ſo little eſteemed, as though nothing neceſſary at all, &amp; yet the meaninge of this ſhorte ſentence, me thinkes I ſhoulde eaſilye vnderſtande, and the rather becauſe I haue hard it oft. I think (to be ſhort) it
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:11754:63"/> is as much to ſay: as, <hi>Nimia familiari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas parit contemptu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> And by this may a ſcholler eaſily vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the meaning and for the inſtruction of the common people, it is as much to ſay, as tomuch familiarity breedeth contempt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Student.</head>
                  <p>Friend Idlenes I ſee you are not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>togeather an ignoraunte, thoughe you confeſſe your ſelfe neuer to bee in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany wher any godnes is taught: as it ſeemeth knowledge comes to you by in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſpiration, but wherof I know not: you haue hit the right way of play<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to a Scholler: but as to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon people, you haue left it as raw as you found it, though you haue ſpoken it in Engliſh, for the ignoraunt &amp; commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> people do as wel vnderſtand Engliſh, for the moſt parte, as they vnderſtande greeke: though ſomtime vnderſtandi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g nothing they verily thinke they vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand all: and vnderſtanding as much as a block, they thinke the greateſt doctor
<pb facs="tcp:11754:64"/> in the world can hardly ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d them, yet they will ſaye, is it not engliſh? and am not I an Engliſh man? why then I pray you may not I vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d it? but it may be aunſweared, are ther not many En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh men ignorauntes? yes, why may not you then be an Engliſh ignorante, but there is an old prouerbe, ignorance is an enemy to knowlege, it is common<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly ſeeme, an ignorant man wil alwaies fynd faults and diſſalow of thoſe things wherein hee hath no ſkill<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, and fyndes a fault where no fault is to be found, and eſpecially when impudency is ioynd vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his ignorance: for then he will profes him ſelf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> before eyther his prince or any wyſe or learned counſaile, thinking his owne wit (when he is a very foole) to be beſt of al? but as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> old ſaying is: who is ſo bould as blynd bayarde? who thinks he knowes more then hee that knowes nothing at al: for the wiſe &amp; learned wil ſay, <hi>hoc ſolum ſcio quod nihil ſcio.</hi> I only know this y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I know nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g at al. And the foole ſayth, what know not I? whereuppon the wiſe man ſayth with
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:11754:64"/> the Phiſition it is time for wiſe men to hold there peace, when euery foole will be a Phiſition. And therfore my friend to make this plain Engliſh more plain as wel vnto you as to the common peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: whereas you ſay, to much familiari<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty breedeth contempt: this is yet as I haue ſaid hard lattine vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple, for it is impoſſible euer to be to fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a wiſe &amp; honeſt ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, how ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore now can this ſentence ſeemetrue in al, ſince it can not be ſometyme to much it can not alwaies breed contempt: and therefore though the ſentence of it ſelfe be true, yet to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding you haue opened it to darkly. y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> plain engliſh is this: to much familiarity bredeth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is, to be checkmate at any time, &amp; haile fellowe to much w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a knaue or a foole, and no doubt hee wil take therby ſuch impude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t courage, as after a while you ſhal fynde to bee moſt true, that he will not greatlye ſticke in anye compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye what ſoeuer, to ſpyt in your mouth when you paſſe the Streetes talkinge
<pb facs="tcp:11754:65"/> with your frend, he wil not be aſhamed to come and colle you about the neck, if you chaunce in frendly manner to geue him but one friendlye worde, or merye looke, you ſhal not fayle of a thouſande agayne, with many a counterfet wrong ſhapen &amp; croked countenaunce if ſo cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſly ſometime by chaunce you enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne him as to ſet him at your borde, you ſhall fynd him ſomtime in your lap when you would wiſh him further of: if at any tyme for your pleaſures ſake, you wil vouchſafe to talke with him in the preſence of his betters. Afterwa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d perhappes when you ſhall be reaſoning with your friend, hee wil be ready with his ſauſy toung to haue a choppe at e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery word that ſhal proceed from your mouth, and thinks it a glory vnto him if he be a meane man, your inferiour a knaue or a foole, that he may ſo boldlye chop logicke with one that is ſo farre aboue him, and his better,</p>
                  <p>And what is the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon ſpeach ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyme of the verieſt knaue in a country? will not he ſay, (being alwayes in quar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rell
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:11754:65"/> and continuall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ar with his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, geuing them oft tymes his own name) the proudeſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>aue of you al ſhal offer mee no wronge, I can goe to my Lorde and to my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>adye, and to the beſt gentleman in the ſhire early or late, to dinner or to ſupper, or at any tyme whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſoeuer I Iuſt, I can ſpeak as boldly vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as I can vnto my fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ltar friend &amp; brother, when a thouſand ſuch drum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medaries and playne knaues, as you be, muſt ſtand at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dore, or if you cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to come in, then with cap in hand, and many a low curteſie. And therfore you playne knaues of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> countrey: how da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e you abuſe me (he might ſay) the capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal and captayne knaue of the worlde: &amp; how can the pore countrey ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> anſwear him ſince oftentymes they fynd and ſee theſe his ſayings to be true. They haue nothing u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the world to ſay, but when y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> knaue is out of ſight, then to whiſper a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge themſelues, and ſay, the more knaue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> better luck: it we could as cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly play y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> knaues, as he, we ſhould eate ſometyme veneſon, and haue other
<pb facs="tcp:11754:66"/> good theere among the beſt, as wel as hee: but ſince our bringing vp hath not bene to beare cunninglye two faces in one hood: or like the ſubtill woulfe, to goe wrapt in a lambes ſkinne, or like a crafty and flatteryng knaue to keepe continuall company among gentlemen in auctoritye and rule, as though hee were the honeſt eſt man in the worlde: wee muſt content our ſelfe as many ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt poore men do, to put vp, daylye in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurye and wronge at manye an arrant knaues hande. The crafty knaue doth continually picke out more friendſhip with his Tounge then the ſimple man euer could with his inforced and lamen table teares. Yet we muſt needes agre that teares at all tymes are not to bee pitied, for often tymes in a man they be token greate diſſemblinge, vnleſſe his cauſe bee the greater, and to a woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſome will ſay they be natural, and take away her teares, take away her lyfe: &amp; therfore the leſſe to be blamed, though ſometyme ſhe weepes for euery tryfle: for wee ſee by experience that ſhe wil
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:11754:66"/> wepe &amp; laugh, and both with one mynd oftentymes very hartely, and that moſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out any diſgrace to her cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite or fauour at all: it ſhewes playnly that ſhe wil ſone be angry &amp; ſoone plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and therin ſhe kepes ſtil y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nature of the ſoft and gentle child, &amp; he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> offers a child wronge, hath but ſmall witt and diſcretion: it hath ſildome bene ſeene, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> mallice coulde neuer ruſt in a womans hart: where it continually ebs &amp; ſlowes there remayneth litle corruption y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall runninge riuers we ſee alwaies moſt cleere at the bottom, &amp; the ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding puddles continually ful of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ilth: caſt as much grauel &amp; ſtones into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one as you can, and ſhortly after with one flow you ſhall ſee it as clean at the bottom as it was before: caſt as much and as litle as you wil into the other, if you come 7. yeare after you ſhal fynd it ſtil at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom. this ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding puddle we ſe is neuer cleane, but once in 7 year it hardly eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes vnfyde, either w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a muckrom or w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a ſwords poynt. The other we ſee it ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually cleer, as it needes not to bee ſide.
<pb facs="tcp:11754:67"/> in the one we ſee duckes and geeſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually ſwilling and bibling for todes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in the other we ſee fiſher me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with their ſiluer hookes continually anglinge for fiſh, with greate paſtime and pleaſure, the one is for the hogge to wallow in &amp; ſometyme for the Oxe and the Cow to drink in, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> other for gentlemen to hake at, &amp; ſometymes perhappes to watter their nagges in: &amp; thus if your eye ſight be any thing clear, you may plainly ſee that teares at a womans eye, be tokens in her a myld and gentle hart, cleare at the bottom from all enuye and malice, though ſometymes perhappes at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt it beginnes of a curſt and a ſhrewiſh ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>make, as for diſgrace which ſometimes it bringes vnto the fauour of her face, it is with women as it is with men: it is a comly ſight in ſome man to looke a loft like a lyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in ſome other it is a thing very vnſeemly.</p>
                  <p>Speech and continuall talking, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth ſome men very wel: few words or rather continuall ſilence, becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth an other man as well, it is a good
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:11754:67"/> ſight to ſee ſome men in coſtly and gor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious apparel, according to the vanity of the tyme, to ſee other ſome it is as good a ſight as to ſee a curre dogge in a ſatten dublet: for a prety ſpaniell it is a great deale better. Is it not a good &amp; commendable ſight to behold ſome ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in his ſide gowne and white ſirples, and euery way beſides in the beſt and moſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly attyre which pertaineth to a graue and diuine miniſter? Doth not a ſhorte coat a payre of hye buckled ſhooes, and a capp with a butten on the crowne, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come an other man as well in his voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (as the countrey huſband man) is it not as good a ſight to ſee an egregi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous offender, and a common breaker of the Princes lawes puniſhed accordinge to his offence, as it is to ſee the obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and true ſubiect, continuallye cheriſhed and made of? to be ſhort, what ſoeuer is thought cumly for an honeſt man, is neuer thought meete for a knaue, and though ſomtime he puts it on it makes hym appeare but a counterfet. Put a beluet coate vppon a knowen naturall,
<pb facs="tcp:11754:68"/> and common foole, is he not more to be laught at then if hee were in his pyde cot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>: bringe an egregious and knowne knaue in place to play the part of an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt man, were it not a thing rather to be laught at then commended? vnleſſe he ment neuer to reuert agayne, which is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ildeme ſeene? in the behauioure of man, there be manye ieſtes, and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience teacheth vs that euery one of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> becomes not euery man alyke. But al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes according to the natural diſpoti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion and bringing vp of the man, they yee de their comly and vncomely grace in him, euen ſo is it (to come vnto my purpoſe) as I haue ſayd amonge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men: for that which doth verye well ſet forth &amp; become one woman, doth as greatlye diſgrace &amp; diſuiger an other. but there a ſtraw: in that I know (as I haue ſayd, women be ſoone angerd, and then without a ſodaine ebbe, theirharts wil ſone ſinck in ſorrow, therfore I wil not meddle to far with them. yet thus much I hope I may boldlye ſay w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the philoſopler, who ſpake more in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:11754:68"/> of the teares of a woman (beyng rightly wayed) then I wil at this tyme vtter, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a teare at ſom woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s eye doth yeelde far more beautifull and comelye grace vnto the fauour of her, then the fayreſt and beſt dyamond that may bee found doth vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pretieſt ring, or moſt pretious iewel in the worlde: and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon that philoſopher ſaid, that a teare in many a womans eye is a pearle in a mans. But leauing the Philoſopher w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all his ſkill, they neuer proceede harte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from them (I think ſurely) with out ſom great cauſe of vnkindnes or greefe. But as is ſaid, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> men no doubt, for the moſt part it is taken for diſſemblinge, &amp; yet ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ſee, they are inforced therto by naturethough it ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not excuſe them. But frend Idlenes, this leads vs with the Lapwing cleane from our matter, touching y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> behauiour of a knaue, &amp; the conſtruction of my late demaunde, and whereunto I haue replyed according to your anſwer, as I haue thought good: for I haue ſhewed you a more playner Conſtruction of the ſentence whiche
<pb facs="tcp:11754:69"/> I putte forth vnto you, then you in my iudgement did make at the firſt &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore now what think you of my conſtruc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion made thereof.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Idlenes.</head>
                  <p>Sir to geue vp ſhortly myne opinion (being very loth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o hinder or interrupt your purpoſe in any ſpech at this time) to my knowlege, you haue opened no more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is true: but whether you haue declared al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truth therof or no I know not.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Student</head>
                  <p>No friende Idlenes I meane not to beate my braynes to open all y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is true, for if I could do ſo I might fill a houſe or rather a whole cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try ful of books, which were vnfit for anye ydle bodye to take in hand. But admittinge (as you haue graunted) that all I haue ſayd is true, I haue ſufficiently obtayned my deſire, for then I hope as you in youre
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:11754:69"/> firſt queſtion propou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded vnto me, crept into my iudgement, by a <hi>ſimile,</hi> &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by (as you ſayd) gathered myne opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in a further matter which ſerued your turne: euen ſo now haue I as well ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued mine, in that you haue confeſſed my conſtruction of the ſentence put forth vnto you, to be true in euery poynt: for now I thinke you wil eaſily ſee &amp; ſoone confeſſe your owne fault.</p>
                  <p>Therfore frend iniury cal your wits togeather, and reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber wel your ſelfe when you firſt tooke occaſion to preſſe your ſelfe into my companye, deſirous as you ſeemed verye friendlye to craue ſometime of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ference with me, finding your ſpeech and behauiour ſo agreable vnto my good lyking, I was content to entertayne &amp; admit you into my ſociety and companye, as heretofore hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared, and to allow of your familiar &amp; boulde ſpeech, as if you had bene my chiefe companion and mate: &amp; now you vau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of your victory, that you haue won me to lye bathinge my ſelfe with you in your laſy and ydle tubbe with your al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g
<pb facs="tcp:11754:70"/> ſweete water of vanity. And now as though I would not wiſh y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding of one hower willinglye without your company: you offer your ſelfe to hange about my necke, as though you were with mee hayle fellowe wel met. But frend ydlenes, when I firſt entertained you (I finde now as a boulde geaſt) I ment nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g leſſe, nor yet do I mind, to wrap you (as gentleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; gentlewome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o their ribonds &amp; chaynes) aboute my neck. I would be loth to be ſene caryi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g you (as begers do their childere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) vpon my back: therfore ſince vpon thys ſmall familiarity vouchſafed vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you (as one of ſhameles childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) you begin to creep vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my backe, no doubt you wil ſhortly fulfil my former ſpeach, to ſpit into my mouth. But friend ydlenes, neither my neck nor my mouth be any fit places for you, I haue otherwayſe to imploy the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: &amp; now ſetting partiality aſide, be your owne iudge whether the old ſaying, to much familiarity breedeth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tempt, be here found true in you or no: and when you know your ſelfe to bee the vayneſt
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:11754:70"/> member in the word, then ſtryue not to dallye any further with me in defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding or anſwearing of any thing, for I mynd no longer to trouble my ſelfe, nor to ſpend any more tyme in hearynge your ydle deuyſes: therfore wher as you ſay, you can feed me with ydle queſtions e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery hower in the day, euery day in the yeare, and euery yeare duryng my lyfe, if I wil but grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t you audience: I wiſh you rather to beſtow them and your ſelfe alſo wher you liſt: and thus in ſtid of audie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce I grant you here my rou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>th. It hath bene an old ſainge, many geeſe many birdes, many wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> many words: but you haue idle talk ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ty for a whole countrey, both of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, therefore ſone as to late, I yeeld vnto you y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> game betimes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Idlenes.</head>
                  <p>If I ſhoulde thus bee lefte at euerye hand, I might wel then go and ſeeke a companion in the Skyes. But this is nothinge ſtraunge vnto mee, for I am
<pb facs="tcp:11754:71"/> ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>times thus baniſhed and ſent away &amp; yet after a while preſently ſometime and priuily intertayned agayn.</p>
                  <p>But ſince now for a tyme I am very lyke to be left here all alone, I wil im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy my ſelf according to the ydlenes of the place.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Idlenes</head>
                  <p>Primus iucu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dus tolle-RANDVS, ATQVE ſecundus tertius eſt vanus: ſed fetat quatridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anus.</p>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <head>Primus.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>VVho geaſtvviſe gape at euery feaſt</l>
                        <l>his hoſt the firſt tyme hartely</l>
                        <l>Sayth vvelcome ſir, among the reſt,</l>
                        <pb n="59" facs="tcp:11754:71"/>
                        <l>and ioyes to feede his fantaſy,</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <head>Secundus.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>But if the ſvveetnes of the fare,</l>
                        <l>glevve ſtil the glutton there to ſtaye,</l>
                        <l>And that he pyne, if he ſhould ſpare</l>
                        <l>to preſſe agayne the like aſſay.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>The goodman then for manners ſake</l>
                        <l>vvil bid him vvelcome as his frend,</l>
                        <l>Content his folly ſo to take,</l>
                        <l>as though ther vvere no more behynd.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <head>Tertius.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>But then if there ſuch roote remayne</l>
                        <l>of ſhameles ſhiftes ſo rype in him</l>
                        <l>As that he can not yet refrayne,</l>
                        <l>But ſtil in follies puddle ſvvim.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>He ſhall the third tyme come in vayne,</l>
                        <l>vvith vvordes of vvelcome none at all,</l>
                        <l>And muſt haue ſcarſely for his payne,</l>
                        <l>one drop of drincke vnleſſe hee call.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <head>Quatridianus.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>The fourth, the fault doth ſmell amayne</l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:11754:72"/>
                        <l>goe place ſyr ſmell roſt then in hall,</l>
                        <l>Or vvith lack drum me him entertayne</l>
                        <l>vvithout the dores vvith dogges to braule.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>His ſtomack ſtampes, as hunger ſlayne,</l>
                        <l>to gorge ſuch geaſtes it is a payne.</l>
                        <l>VVho vviſely can himſelfe ſo ſtrayne</l>
                        <l>to match ſuch mates ſhall greatly gayne</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>For novv ſuch ſuckpaps olde do <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>aygne,</l>
                        <l>vvhich after dugges that drop good chea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </l>
                        <l>Do ſo much dayly fond and fayne,</l>
                        <l>as no place can from them be cleere,</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>For wearing of ringes.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>FOr that it is a prouerbe olde,</l>
                     <l>the vvinners may beſt vveare the gold</l>
                     <l>VVe knubby knuckels ruſty rough</l>
                     <l>do ſee more fit to lead the plough,</l>
                     <l>VVhich fond to ſee their fingers ſhyne,</l>
                     <l>in ſteede of fatt, vvith goulden myne</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But vviſely vvayed it is moſt vayne</l>
                     <l>and bringes ſuch thinges in geat diſdayne,</l>
                     <l>VVhen ringes be knackes for euery knaue</l>
                     <l>for then no vviſemen vvil them craue</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb n="60" facs="tcp:11754:72"/>
                     <l>But vvere it trim to ring the noſe</l>
                     <l>I thinke I might ſoone fynd out thoſe</l>
                     <l>That vvould to pleaſe their daynty gyrles</l>
                     <l>rend that vvith ringe and pretious pearles.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Diſorder marreth euery thinge</l>
                     <l>ſo doth miſvvearyng of your ringe,</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Coſt is comly vvher order is</l>
                     <l>good order therfore ſhould not miſſe</l>
                     <l>And ſuch as vveare them as they ought</l>
                     <l>the vvorthier then ſhall they be thought</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But ſome men thinke and ſo do I</l>
                     <l>that natures fleſh vvhen it is bare,</l>
                     <l>VVithout ſuch pearles or paultery</l>
                     <l>if fayre, is fitteſt for the glare.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>For vvhen dame Venus playnly ſhovves</l>
                     <l>her ſelfe in natures naked vveed</l>
                     <l>Your eyes then flye not after crovves,</l>
                     <l>but ſlayes to feede your vvanton neede.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>To this the vviſeſt men of all</l>
                     <l>As vve ſee dayly they be thrall</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But as for pearles of pretious ſtones</l>
                     <l>they paſſe not for they be but toyes,</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:11754:73"/>
                     <l>And gaudy geaugavves for the nones,</l>
                     <l>vvhich they accompt as childiſh ioyes.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But ſince they haue bene greatly vſd</l>
                     <l>though much perhappes by ſome abuſd</l>
                     <l>It is not good to take avvaye</l>
                     <l>ſuch comly coſtly gold array.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But vvho ſo vſeth it aright</l>
                     <l>reſerues the thumbe as for the knight</l>
                     <l>And here in order as they lye,</l>
                     <l>your finger rynges you may apply.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>Miles, Marcator, Stultus, nuptie, &amp; amator.</p>
                  <p>☞ ☜</p>
                  <q>
                     <p>To vveare the ringe vpon the thum is for the Knight.</p>
                     <p>The forefinger for the Marchaunt.</p>
                     <p>The middle finger for the Foole</p>
                     <pb n="61" facs="tcp:11754:73"/>
                     <p>The third finger for the maried man.</p>
                     <p>The little finger for the Louer.</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>☞ ☜</p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The Knight ſayth in his ring,</l>
                     <l>no vaunt to victory.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The Marchaunt in his.</l>
                     <l>no foe to Fortune.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The Foole in his</l>
                     <l>no coſt to colours.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The Maryed man in his</l>
                     <l>no iarre to ielouſy.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The louer in his</l>
                     <l>no friende to fayth.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="1">
                     <head>1</head>
                     <l>The Knight in field in armour clad,</l>
                     <l>in eye of foes vvhich fayne his fall</l>
                     <l>He ſayth he ſighes vvhen truſe is had:</l>
                     <l>no vaunt to victory great or ſmall.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:11754:74"/>
                     <l>2 The marchant ſaylyng in his Ship,</l>
                     <l>VVith trafficke far and neere for gayne,</l>
                     <l>Still doubring leſt he once ſhould ſlip,</l>
                     <l>no foe to fortune ſayth he playne.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>3 The Foole in folly fettered faſt,</l>
                     <l>led forth fond fancyes moſt to craue</l>
                     <l>He cares not vvhat doth vvaſt or laſt.</l>
                     <l>no coſt to colours (ſayth he) braue.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>4. The maried man great griefes indure,</l>
                     <l>and oft his hart nevv panges ſupply,</l>
                     <l>And yet nothing can him allure</l>
                     <l>but ſayth no iar to ielouſye,</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>5 The louer liues and reapes the ioyes</l>
                     <l>of all the vvorlde, and thus he ſayth</l>
                     <l>VVhere true loue lackes the reſt be ioyes</l>
                     <l>the earth doth beare no friend to fayth.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The rich man reſtles loth to heare</l>
                     <l>of all ſortes ſome to ſpeake theire mynde.</l>
                     <l>And he to ſeeme of couldeſt cheere.</l>
                     <l>VVho can them all in vvealth outvvinde.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Sayth (tumbling vp his ruſty bagges</l>
                     <l>loth to ſee his gliſtering gould</l>
                     <l>Abroad to flye lyke tattered ragges)</l>
                     <l>no vvoe to vvant vvhen I am old.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:11754:74"/>
                  <head>The Kinge. Omnes vos defendo. <hi>I defend you all.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The king and ruler of the Realme</l>
                     <l>by ſtrength of ſvvord and counſayle grau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>Shrinkes not to ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ryue agaynſt a ſtreame</l>
                     <l>from furious force his ſeate to ſaue.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>He neuer quayles nor fightes in feare</l>
                     <l>his hand and hart alvvayes agree,</l>
                     <l>No force of armes that man can beare.</l>
                     <l>can ſtay vvhat he intendes to bee.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The ſtrongeſt ſtreames of riuers vvide</l>
                     <l>by Princely povver are made to fall,</l>
                     <l>They ſtop not him to goe or ryde</l>
                     <l>for bredth or depth, his foes to gall.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>VVhat caſtle, tovver, or ſtrongeſt hold</l>
                     <l>yeelds not in vievv of princely force,</l>
                     <l>And ſtoupes vvith crackes as vveake &amp; ould</l>
                     <l>to geue him vvay to take his courſe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>And graunt him, though a countrey ſmall</l>
                     <l>of truſty ſtrong and faythful hartes</l>
                     <l>He neuer feares as once to fal,</l>
                     <l>though all the vvorld beſides take parts</l>
                  </lg>
                  <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11754:75"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The earth the ſubſtance is of man</l>
                     <l>from vvhence all creatures firſt vvere made</l>
                     <l>And thence our liuely fode began.</l>
                     <l>novv mayntaynd by this golden trade.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>VVhich once let ſlacke but for a vvhyle</l>
                     <l>it ſhortly after vvil appeare.</l>
                     <l>VVho is moſt vviſe vvil vſe leaſt vvile</l>
                     <l>and ſhal moſt ſone ſhevv couldeſt cheere.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>And therfore thus among the reſt</l>
                     <l>to ſpeake the truth he may be bould</l>
                     <l>That from the vvorſt vnto the beſt</l>
                     <l>hee feedes all ſortes both younge and olde.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The Phiſition.</l>
                     <l>Omnes vos edo.</l>
                     <l>I eate you all.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>VVhere liberall Artes do all take roote</l>
                     <l>from thence Phifitions moſt do ſpring<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>A trade vvhich if they vvin, doth boo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e</l>
                     <l>them greatly all, much vveath to bringe</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>He <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>vholly lyeues vpon his art,</l>
                     <l>VVh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> all his age</l>
                     <l>He hath no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> mart</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> aſſvvage.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb n="64" facs="tcp:11754:75"/>
                     <l>VVhich doth all ſortes of men ſo vvring</l>
                     <l>as fevv or none can lacke him long.</l>
                     <l>And vvhere the empty purſes cling</l>
                     <l>they muſt abyde the paynful prong</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>For if he ſhould of pitty ſpend</l>
                     <l>VVith all poore payned ſoules his tyme,</l>
                     <l>He might himſelfe to begging bend,</l>
                     <l>vvhich vvere in him a haynous crime.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But rich or pore vvho hath a grote,</l>
                     <l>though he perhaps be hunger ſlayne,</l>
                     <l>That vvil not keepe it from his throte</l>
                     <l>to eaſe his heauy hart of payne.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>VVhereto he oft vvith grieued mynd</l>
                     <l>ſees men ſo driuen all to ſpende</l>
                     <l>And ſparing not to ſpeake his kind</l>
                     <l>ſayth he eates all vp at the end.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The light woman.</l>
                     <l>Omnes vos decipio.</l>
                     <l>I deceaue you all.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>This vvoman is by natures ſhape,</l>
                     <l>and forme to ſight ſo beautifull</l>
                     <l>As happy he vvhoſe eyes eſcape</l>
                     <l>moſt cleanly there to take a pull.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:11754:76"/>
                     <l>He neuer any tenant ſkeare,</l>
                     <l>before the cheefeſt lord of all,</l>
                     <l>Commaund him as his meſſinger,</l>
                     <l>ſuch tenant to his Lord to call</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>And then he comes to him in ſpeede</l>
                     <l>vvith ſuch a doleful deadly ſound,</l>
                     <l>VVhich makes the ſtrongeſt harte to bleede,</l>
                     <l>and yeeld his body to the grounde.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>He ſpare<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>no king for all his ſtrength,</l>
                     <l>nor any man for pollicy</l>
                     <l>Nor VVoman for beauty at the length</l>
                     <l>but calles in time them all to dye.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Therfore my harueſt tyme ſayth he,</l>
                     <l>doth neuer ceaſe ſome vvhere to fall</l>
                     <l>But <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ype, or rotten as you be,</l>
                     <l>my cyth in fyne cleare ſheeres dovvne all<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <head>Youthful age.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>But youthful age, thus death doe blame,</l>
                        <l>And ſhootes this boult vvith vvanton aime,</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>That vvere I Death or Death could be</l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:11754:76"/>
                        <l>and vvere I then as I am novv,</l>
                        <l>Fayre vvomen ſure ſhould ſyldome dye</l>
                        <l>vntil their age did make them bovv.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>If Death did manlike deale his dole,</l>
                        <l>he could not ſhevv that cruelty</l>
                        <l>To hayle ſuch into vgly hole</l>
                        <l>vvhich loke on him ſo pitiouſly.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>But vvantons ſome perhaps vvil ſay</l>
                        <l>that vvomen they haue hartes moſt ſtrong</l>
                        <l>And oft ſing merily careavvay</l>
                        <l>ſoone after many a paynful prong,</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>VVhich can not vvell vvith reaſon be,</l>
                        <l>fince dayly ſight doth teach vs this,</l>
                        <l>They neuer naked vveapon ſee</l>
                        <l>but ſtreyght they faynt vvorſe ſkeard then hur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Her ſtrenghe of body is moſt ſmall</l>
                        <l>the vveakeſt man that may be founde</l>
                        <l>If any ſtrength he hath at all,</l>
                        <l>ſoone tryps her dovvne, ſhe treades ſo ligh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Therfore me thinkes great reaſon might<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </l>
                        <l>perſvvade this raging Death to ſpare</l>
                        <l>Such vveaklinges from that paynfull plight,</l>
                        <l>to choke them vvith ſuch ſovver fare.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <pb facs="tcp:11754:77"/>
                        <l>Then can by arte be vvel diſplayde,</l>
                        <l>to Death claymes neere affinity</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Therefore the louer rightly ſayde</l>
                        <l>and can by none be vvel denayed</l>
                        <l>That ſure it is a deadly payne</l>
                        <l>to loue and not be loued agayne.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>And nere thervvith I make an end</l>
                        <l>true loue is ſure a faythful friende,</l>
                        <l>VVhen true loue parts it is a death</l>
                        <l>though ſtil in breaſt remaynes the breath.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>More liuing deathes I might vvell name</l>
                        <l>vvhich kepes mans life in death like frame</l>
                        <l>VVhen clouniſh clookes of knaues preuaile</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>o force the guiltles hartes to quaile.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>But the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e a ſtravv till leaſure ſerue,</l>
                        <l>ſuch clovvnlike ſhape in braſſe to carue</l>
                        <l>And thus to knitt the finall knot</l>
                        <l>death ſtil vvil be the latter lot,</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>The vvhich God graunt all men may dravv,</l>
                        <l>vvith price of euerlaſting ioy,</l>
                        <l>And then their debts be dubble payd,</l>
                        <l>vvhom novv the vvorldly vvronges annoy.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:11754:77"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Mors tua, mors Chriſti.</l>
               <l>Fraus mundi gloria coe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i.</l>
               <l>Et dolor inferni,</l>
               <l>Sunt meditanda tibi.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>That Chriſt did die, that thou muſt die,</l>
               <l>the vvorldly fraude, the heauenly ioy,</l>
               <l>The endles bitter paines of hell,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oſſe them (as tenis balles) in minde,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But hereat ſome perhaps vvill ſticke,</l>
               <l>and ſay, vvho alvvaies thinkes of death</l>
               <l>Shal neuer looke vvith chearefull face,</l>
               <l>but ſvva<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>te, and vvan, and halfe as dead.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>VVhereby appeares, vvhome nature hath</l>
               <l>forbidden beauties ſiluer ſhovv,</l>
               <l>To good more prone and ready be,</l>
               <l>then they vvhom nature hath decoerd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The one <hi>I</hi> vvill not maſerate</l>
               <l>ſaith he my plumround phyſnomie</l>
               <l>My ſtraight made lim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> I vvill not crooke</l>
               <l>to thinke of death, of deuill, or God,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The other ſaith my fauour is harde,</l>
               <l>my body croukie, of all deſpiſde,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11754:78"/>
               <l>The vvorld I leaue it loues not me</l>
               <l>I ioy to thinke on heauenly thinges.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The happy bleſſed man</l>
               <l>doth loth this vvorldly life.</l>
               <l>The vvicked ſtryues in vvhat he can,</l>
               <l>to vvhet ſtill pleaſures knife.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The vvicked vvighte bevvayles the ſight</l>
               <l>of deadly naked dart:</l>
               <l>To bleſſed plight it bringes delight,</l>
               <l>vvho gently yeeldes his hart,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Vita principium mortis,</l>
               <l>Mors vltima linia rerum.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Lyfe is the firſt begynning</l>
               <l>of Death, and death the</l>
               <l>laſt end of all.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Man peepes no ſooner out</l>
               <l>his vitall breath to take,</l>
               <l>But death him compaſſe round aboute</l>
               <l>his ſubiect ſtrayght to make</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11754:78"/>
               <l>By ſpeech or pen the buſy men</l>
               <l>VVho moſt in vvordes delight.</l>
               <l>Muſt needes afford the laſt cold vvorde</l>
               <l>to death vvhich is his right.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="compositor_to_the_reader">
            <head>The Compoſitor to the Auctour.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>AS tyme doth teach and rule the roming mynd,</l>
               <l>So tyme hath brought thy toyling taſke to ende:</l>
               <l>As tyme hath licenſt vs to ſeeke and fynd,</l>
               <l>So tyme doth warne vs compt thee as a frend:</l>
               <l>And ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th thou toyes thy Golden tyme to ſpend</l>
               <l>For Countries ſake ſome profite pure to be,</l>
               <l>Tyme warnes vs all due thankes to render thee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Who merits fame, renowne, or laſting prayſe</l>
               <l>But onely thoſe that toyle in Countryes cauſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>Who beares the bell in theſe our diſmall dayes,</l>
               <l>But they which can diſcribe the curious clauſe?</l>
               <l>Therfore poſt on my pen and do not pauſe.</l>
               <l>Till thou haſt playd with ſpeede a thankeful part</l>
               <l>To lawde and prayſe the Authors willinge h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11754:79"/>
               <l>You muſing myndes that murmur in delight,</l>
               <l>Come lend your Eares to heare a word or twayne,</l>
               <l>Turne backe one leafe, caſt of all hateful ſpyte,</l>
               <l>To learne this leſſon do not now diſdayne:</l>
               <l>Do you not know what hateful wordes do gayne?</l>
               <l>Be of good cheere O <hi>Thimelthorpe</hi> I pray,</l>
               <l>Paſſe not a pin what prating Parrats ſay.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thou ſowed haſt the ſeede for vs to reape,</l>
               <l>We of thy toyle the ſugred ſweete do taſte:</l>
               <l>And ſith it comes to all of vs ſo cheape,</l>
               <l>Therof we wil not wantonly make waſt:</l>
               <l>A friendly looke in fayth the wyſe will caſt,</l>
               <l>For that is all I know that thou doſt craue,</l>
               <l>A thouſand thankes therfore be ſure to haue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For Memus mates, or for their fury fell,</l>
               <l>Paſſe not a whit, eſteeme them as they are:</l>
               <l>Let them goe bathe in Lymbo lake of hell:</l>
               <l>Thy fame ſhall liue for euer take no care:</l>
               <l>And if that I could learnedly prepare</l>
               <l>My pen to paynt out verſes pure and braue,</l>
               <l>Thy name ſhould liue when corps lye cloeſd in graue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet I which haue but weake and ſimple ſkill,</l>
               <l>Can well diſcerne the good from bad I know,</l>
               <l>The wyſer ſort when they haue viewd their ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll</l>
               <l>And toſt this Pamphlet ouer too and froe,</l>
               <l>I ken my ſelfe what count'naunce they w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſhow:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11754:79"/>
               <l>The faultes therein the'il not impute to thee,</l>
               <l>But iudge the Printers preſſe in part to be,</l>
            </lg>
            <div type="to_the_reader">
               <head>To the Reader,</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>Good Reader, ſyth thou haſt peruſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e the ſame,</l>
                  <l>And mayſt agayne at pleaſure thyne behould</l>
                  <l>It faultes thou fynd the Auctor do not blame,</l>
                  <l>No furious word agaynſt him do vnfold,</l>
                  <l>But (vſe thy pen) in mending ought be bould,</l>
                  <l>A wryter ſure as yet he is but young,</l>
                  <l>Therefore to laude him exerciſe thy toung.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>So wilt thou win the worthy prayſe of all</l>
                  <l>That here among graue wryters do remayne.</l>
                  <l>Of gentle bloud accompt thee ſure wee ſhall,</l>
                  <l>Flye far from taunts which ſtill thy name doth ſtaine,</l>
                  <l>And from the face of falſe enuyous trayne,</l>
                  <l>Eke call to mynd what Volumes ſtill we ſee,</l>
                  <l>That ſafe from faultes can not excuſed bee.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Learned man will ſee, and litle ſay,</l>
                  <l>The witles w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ght his toung lyes neuer ſtill.</l>
                  <l>A good report if wyſe men ſhew alway,</l>
                  <l>Let prating peyſauntes prattle what they will.</l>
                  <l>When they their venim haue ſpewd out their fyll,</l>
                  <l>The wyſe will iudge what folly merits then</l>
                  <l>And who doth purchaſe prayſe the beſt of men.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <trailer>Finis, R S.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
